<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Meditations vpon Psal. 101. Written first in French, by Philip Mornai lord of Plessis, and by him dedicated to Henrie the fourth, the French king. And now translated into English, for the benefit of the christian reader, by T.W.</title>
            <title>Meditations upon Psal. 101.</title>
            <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106486</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842201</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842201</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6835</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07767)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6835)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 641:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Meditations vpon Psal. 101. Written first in French, by Philip Mornai lord of Plessis, and by him dedicated to Henrie the fourth, the French king. And now translated into English, for the benefit of the christian reader, by T.W.</title>
                  <title>Meditations upon Psal. 101.</title>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 174 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Adam Islip for Thomas Man, dwelling in Paternoster row, at the signe of the Talbot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Wilcox (trans.).</note>
                  <note>A translation, by Thomas Wilcox, of the French original of Philippe de Mornay.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: leaf E5 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms --  Criticism, interpretation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6835:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6835:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MEDITATIONS <hi>vpon Pſal.</hi> 101.</p>
            <p>Written firſt in French, by PHILIP MORNAI lord of Pleſſis, and by him dedicated to Henrie the fourth, the French king.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now tranſlated into Engliſh, for the benefit of the Chriſtian Reader, by</hi> T. W.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Adam Iſlip for Thomas Man, dwelling in Paternoſter row, at the ſigne of the Talbot. 1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6835:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6835:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right Honourable and his verie good Lord, the L.</hi> Robert, Earle of Eſſex, &amp;c. L. high Marſhall of England, &amp;c. and now L. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of hir Maieſties forces, appointed for the reducing of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, to former, yea and to more faithfull obedience than heretofore. T. W. wiſheth all proſperitie and bleſſedneſſe thorow Christ, both now and for euer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue (right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) an old ſaying amongſt vs: <hi>He gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth twiſe that giueth quickly.</hi> And the ſpirit (which is both antiquitie and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie it ſelfe) ſaith: <hi>A word ſpoken in his place is like apples of gold with pictures of ſiluer.</hi> How fitly this wil agree with other mens actions
<pb facs="tcp:6835:3"/>and my preſent practiſe, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther others, and your L. eſpecially ſhould iudge and feele than my ſelfe ſpeake. This I am ſure of, that as hertofore many times you haue by ſundrie perſons ben preſented with great varietie of vvordes and workes: ſo now particularly vpon your going out againſt the Iriſh rebels, you haue, and ſhal haue the like performed, becauſe as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Many doe ſeeke the face of the ruler.</hi> I ſay againe, how fitly theſe haue bene, or are accompliſhed, as alſo with vvhat affections men do them, that is known to God alone <hi>who is the onely ſearcher of the heart and reins.</hi> And yet I doubt not, but that your L. is indued with grace from aboue, in ſome meaſure to practiſe that in your ſelfe, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards other, which the holy ghoſt
<pb facs="tcp:6835:3"/>ſpeaketh: <hi>Though councell in the heart of man is like deepe waters, yet a man that hath vnderstanding will draw it out.</hi> I vvill leaue others to the Lord, <hi>before whome they muſt ſtand or fall,</hi> vvhoſoeuer they be, for vvho am I that I ſhould iudge or iuſtifie any, ſith that office be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the Lord alone? But touching my ſelfe, it is ynough for me, that I know mine owne heart, and that I can in ſome ſort &amp; ſence truelie ſay, as the Apoſtle dooth: <hi>This is our reioicing, the teſtimonie of our conſcience,</hi> that as in other things, ſo in this that I now doe, <hi>I walke not according to fleſhly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but in ſimplicitie and godly pureneſſe.</hi> Many ſend your L. men and monie, horſſe and armor, and many good thinges beſides, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the furniſhing and ſetting of
<pb facs="tcp:6835:4"/>you forward in this great and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble voiage: yea ſundrie are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to aduenture as it vvere their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and perſons vvith you in this vvorthie ſeruice. All theſe thinges no doubt of it, are good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; may be true teſtimonies of ſincere affection in your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers and fauourits, yea they may be powerfull meanes of iuſt defence for you and yours, &amp; our whole ſtate, &amp; of lawful annoiance and confuſion vpon the enemies againſt vvhom you goe. But take heede my L. that theſe cauſe you not to be puffed vp in your ſelfe, and ſo to go forth <hi>in the arm of fleſh and bloud.</hi> The thing that you ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are eſpeciallie to regard ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is, that they bee thankefullie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, as from God, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie vſed as in regarde of your
<pb facs="tcp:6835:4"/>ſelfe, and thoſe that ſhall aſsiſt you, and be at your command. Outward and humane helpes, my ſelfe haue not to preſent, but may rather ſay vvith the Apoſtle, <hi>Siluer and gold haue I none: ſuch as I haue, ſuch I giue.</hi> And yet let not I beſeech you, my vvant of vvorld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie things, make leſſe precious in your iudgement, the ſpiritual gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that God is pleaſed by me the vnworthieſt of his ſeruants, at this time to offer vnto you: for this I can and dare aſſure you, euen in the vvord of truth and life (vvhich is more than the vvords of all mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men in the vvorld, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great) that though it be lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in outward appearance, and weak according to vvorldlie ſhew: yet if it be thorowlie ſetled in you for knowledge, and continuallie
<pb facs="tcp:6835:5"/>obſerued for practiſe, it vvil be not onlie as good as the moſt or beſt outward things that you carie with you, but a vvorthie mean to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all &amp; euerie one of them to you &amp; others: yea it vvil make your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out glorious, &amp; your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in again proſperous &amp; ful of renown (a matter that manie I am ſure, wiſh and praie for vvith all their harts) <hi>as which indeed wil watch for you when you ſleepe,</hi> &amp; vvill vphold your cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit at home, &amp; perſon abroad, yea and preſerue you &amp; yours, though you ſhould come vnto the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt danger &amp; diſtreſſe that could be. In al this great praiſe of the thing it ſelfe, I neither praiſe mine owne paine, I proteſt, nor prouide for my commendation in the vvorld, nor couetouſlie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cunninglie ſeeke gifts from your L. But dutifullie
<pb facs="tcp:6835:5"/>thereby to prouoke your L. care to diligent reading thereof, and carefullie to ſtir you vp to dailie performance of ſuch good things as are propounded therin. Your high place and perſon, your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and holie profeſsion, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie and vveightie cauſes that you muſt manage, the manifold perils that thereby you may preuent, the ſingular good that thereby you ſhall atcheeue, vvith ſundrie ſuch like, ſhou1d I am ſure, and I doubt not but they vvill prouoke ſincere obedience. Wherof I truſt your L. vvill haue no vvhit the leſſe regard, euen in this reſpect, becauſe that I for my part ſhall think my care, my labour, my loue, and vvhatſoeuer dutie I haue done or may doe vnto your L. to be ſufficientlie recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced, if theſe poore trauails may
<pb facs="tcp:6835:6"/>find good acceptance vvith you, and patronage from you, and in you may bring forth theſe good and gracious effects. And ſo hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie beſeeching the Lord merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to direct you in all affaires that you ſhall take in hand, according to his holie vvil, &amp; namelie to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper this preſent and ſo important ſeruice, for Gods glorie, the welfare of our kingdomes, her Maieſties Chriſtian comfort &amp; peace euerie manner of vvaie, your owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular good, and the confuſion and ouerthrow of al Gods, the eſtates, her Maieſties, and your ovvn ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I humblie take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At London <date>the ſecond of March, 1599.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors very humble, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to bee commanded in all Chriſtian dutie.</hi> T. Wilcocks <hi>the Lords vnworthy ſeruant.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6835:6"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Readers, grace and peace from God, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beſeech you all, of what ſtate ſoeuer, with carefull attendance, and ſerious thoughts, to view and read ouer this Treatiſe following. This motion I make, not for any doubt or ſuſpition J haue of any vnſound matter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for J am perſuaded it containeth in it the truth of God: But becauſe I am acquainted with, or at the leaſt wiſe not ignorant of thoſe ordinarie ſtops and lets, that hinder our growth in goodnes by good things, as Sathans malice, our blind and ignorant harts, our careleſſe minds, diſcouragements from others, and ſundrie ſuch like: by means whereof, men are many times miſseled: and becauſe alſo I am ſure
<pb facs="tcp:6835:7"/>theſe things may, nay will fall out, in peruſing and reading euen the beſt things, I can not but againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine entreat you herein alſo to haue a good eye to your ſelues and your own ſoules. Aſſuredly you ſhall find (ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if you weigh things well, as in deed you ſhould) that you haue great and good cauſe ſo to doe: for beſides that the points handled therin are not meane, neither of any ſimple ſubiect, and therefore would be regarded and receiued with care and conſcience of them: the very manner of handling of them (according to the vſuall courſe and practiſe of the Author) is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and pithie, and therefore alſo will require a diligent and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding heart: The treatie was firſt written in French by a worthy Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of that country, and therfore doth most properly appertain to that ſtate.
<pb facs="tcp:6835:7"/>That which peculiarly belongeth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, vnderſtand it of, and referre it to the ſame. The reſt that is common, and according to general truth, make com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but yet good vſe withall of it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. And this premonition I think ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meet to giue, as knowing before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand how ready men are to ſnatch and catch at that which belongeth not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, their times, and ſtates: a point arguing great curioſitie, and no ſmall lightneſse of mind, and lacke of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: as alſo careleſly to neglect, yea ſecurely to contemne that which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth them much, a matter bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing careleſnes at the leaſt, if not ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe of heart; from both which, as all other extreames, I wiſh the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an reader, as my ſelfe, in this and in all other things of the like nature, to be freed and purged, and on the other ſide to be fulfilled with all ſound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:6835:8"/>and carefulneſse of ſpirit, that ſo from this and other good things, we may alwaies learne to know what that good, holy, and acceptable will of his is, and may be enabled by the bleſsed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, stedfaſtly to beleeue the ſame, and carefully to walk in the obedience ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Now the very God of peace ſanctifie you thorowout: and I pray alſo, that your whole ſpirit and ſoule, and bodie, may be kept blameleſſe, vntill the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to whom euery where, but ſpecially in the church, be praiſe for euer &amp; euer. Sobeit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours euer in Chriſt. <hi>T. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="meditation_on_Psalm_n101">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6835:8"/>
            <head>Lord Ieſus begin, and make an end.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>En who are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to frame their faces, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances, doe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily go to glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and indeuour to ſet them therby: but Kings for the direction of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and affaires, had much more need to looke thereinto, as well becauſe their callings are more high and heauie than other mens, as alſo becauſe they haue more lets from themſelues, and others that be about the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to hinder their ſight. And therefore they had need to haue, (if they could tell how) more liuely and
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6835:9"/>then you ſhall indeed ſurely raigne, when you moſt ſoundly ſerue him. Wherin, if euen the beſt princes haue at ſundry times ben not only admoniſhed, but threatened with the wrath and diſpleaſure of God, and all to preuent theſe euils in them, that they might not fall away from their dutie, or abuſe his mercie, patience, and long ſuffering, you (Sir) nor others, muſt thinke much to be often called vpon, yea prouoked and whetted on, to theſe good things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none runneth ſo faſt, but hee had need to be incour aged,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>So to runne, that he may attaine:</hi> neither ſtandeth ſo ſure, but he had need to bee admoniſhed, and put in mind of the Apoſtles ſpeech,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.10.</note> 
               <hi>Let him that thinketh hee ſtandeth, take heed leaſt he fall,</hi> and withall to remember the ſaying of this very kingly Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>I ſaid in my proſperitie, I ſhall neuer be moued, but when thou diddeſt hide thy face, I was ſore troubled.</hi> For this is a certaine and an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured point, That men are in more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be ouerthrowne, yea ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when they enioy abundance of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6835:9"/>graces from God, than when they are vnder his chaſtiſements and correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For as for chaſtiſements, euen then when they beat downe men in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they lift them vp before God, and make them by conſequent capable and meet to receiue his mercies: and that is it the Apoſtle meaneth, when he ſaith, <hi>They doe in the end bring with them the quiet fruit of righteouſnes vnto them which are thereby exerciſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 12.11.</note> Whereas graces on the other ſide, in Gods purpoſe indeed, and their owne nature, carrying men out of themſelues vnto God, cauſe them notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, throgh Sathans malice, and the corruption of their own hearts, to deſpiſe almightie God himſelfe, and to ſay <hi>Who is the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 30.9.</note> and ſo make them to become fit matter, vpon whome to exerciſe and execute the ſeueritie of his rigour and wrath, for the contempt or abuſe of ſo ſingular graces.</p>
            <p>Men much trouble themſelues (Sir) now a daies to defend and maintain your calling and comming to the crowne. But iwis it needeth not, for your verie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6835:10"/>birth alone is ſufficient to intitle you thereto. But to come to it, to come tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly to it, yea to come to the top of it, and to carrie your ſelfe therein as is moſt meet, there is indeed, and there muſt bee indeed, required a farre other thing: and that is, a great aſcendent, as men vſe to ſay, and a gracious aſpect and direction thereof, fauouring this birth of yours, and being able to correct all contrarie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtellations, yea euerie thing that either directly or indirectly might annoy you with his influence. That which I meane, is not any ſtarre or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, or anie whole zodiake, as they vſe to ſay, no not heauen it ſelfe, or the heauen of heauens, but indeed the ſoueraigne God, <hi>the only Lord, maker and creatour of all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 38.31.32.33.</note> 
               <hi>who loſeth</hi> (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) <hi>the power of the ſtarres, and ordereth the gouernment of the heauens aboue the earth: by whome</hi> (as alſo ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>Kings raigne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pr. 8.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>and Gouernors keepe their eſtate:</hi> and by whom you (Sir) may ſay, as this our King <hi>Dauid</hi> doth, <hi>The Lord is with me, I ſhal raign and rule: againſt him there is neither counſelnor
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6835:10"/>ſtrength: wherefore nothing in the world can ſhake me or make me to be moued.</hi> Wee that liue in the cleare light of Gods word, wonder at the conceits that in the times of blindneſſe and ſuperſtition men haue thruſt one another into. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologians made Princes in former time beleeue, that ſuch or ſuch a pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net bare rule ouer their birth. They perſuaded otherſome, that a certain ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit aſſiſted them, for the guidance, line, or leading of their life. And it is as ſtrange to conſider what dotages theſe deceiued perſons fell into: and that not only the baſeſt of the people, but the beſt amongſt men: for euen the very Princes themſelues honored theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, and they did exactly obſerue what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they thought would pleaſe their inſtructers, planets, ſpirits, and ſuch like: and vtterly abhorred whatſoeuer might anie manner of way offend or diſpleaſe them. But you (Sir) haue much more ſtrong reaſon to ſtriue to pleaſe God, and to ſeeke to ſerue him: for theſe were but fantaſies of their own framing,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6835:11"/>whereas God liueth in himſelfe, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnto you and al others,<note place="margin">Acts. 17.28.</note> 
               <hi>Life, breath, and being.</hi> Greeue not therefore at anie hand, or in anie ſort I beſeech you, this great aſcendant, who is your almightie, and your moſt mercifull gouernour. He requireth of men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.27.</note> 
               <hi>that they follow vertue, and that they flie vice:</hi> &amp; this (ſo gracious is he vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) doth he for their own ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and good. Of Kings he demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that they plant pietie, that they render righteouſneſſe. What more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable taxe or impoſition could hee lay vpon them? This is a gentle tribute indeed, and a ſweet ſeruitude, if I may ſo call it. Nay it is the onely meane to rule bleſſedly and well, and therefore ſhould be the more carefully ſtriuen to. And of you certainely (Sir) ſo much the more carefully to be performed, becauſe hee hath done more for you, than for ſundry Kings beſides, yea ſo much the more, by how much hee hath declared to you the gracious eie of a louing father, and not the wrathfull face of an angrie Maiſter, as hee did to ſundrie your predeceſſors.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6835:11"/>But it is now good time to leaue you, and to heare <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe ſpeake, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> I ſay, pronouncing his vow vnto God, euen then when he firſt entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his kingdome.</p>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 1.</hi> I will ſing <hi>(ſaith hee)</hi> Mercie and Iuſtices O eternall God, I will ſing them to thee.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Auid</hi> a warlike Prince, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, if euer there were any, wanted not matter here to ſing, after the manner of prophane and heathen princes, his triumphs and victories: for he had vanquiſhed ſtrangers abroad, and rebels at home, he had done very famous acts of a worthy captaine and valiant ſouldier, yea therein hee had proceeded ſo farre, that the princes and nobles of his kingdome were inforced to preſent a ſolemne ſupplication vnto him, that hee would no more hazard or indanger his perſon,<note place="margin">2. Sa. 21.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Leaſt they might ſee the light
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6835:12"/>of Iſrael put out.</hi> A man would thinke then, that hee ſhould haue made a vow, and haue ſet out his valour, and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his armour and weapons, and haue exalted them: but being ſpiritually min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at this time, he was farre from the thoughts of theſe wordly things. And though for the firſt inſtruction of a Prince, he might as a man would ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, haue taught him to haue ben har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and courageous, yet he was conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to omit all that, and to come to deale with matters of greater conſequence. For though I will not denie, but confeſſe rather, that it is a vertue very profitable for all great Princes, and for <hi>Dauid</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more neceſſarie than for others, who had ſpent the whole courſe of his life, as well in warres againſt them that lay nigh vnto him, as in compounding inward troubles at home: yet hee will as it were in ſilence for the time, paſſe by all theſe things, and ſing of, and exalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them all, <hi>this benignitie</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>and iuſtice,</hi> Mercie &amp; Iudgement. Now to ſing them, what is it, but to publiſh
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6835:12"/>them, and to cauſe them to ſound and ſhine forth, yea to ſound them forth euery where, to ſpread them abroad, and to diſtribute them into all the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and corners of his kingdome? And good reaſon it ſhould bee ſo, becauſe they are indeed the two daughters of holy and heauenly wiſedome, <hi>by which kings raign:</hi> yea they are two ſpecial qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, by which God manifeſteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto men, and by which hee will haue his lawfull lieutenants knowne amongſt men, and bee marked. For take them away once, and how can publike perſons be ſaid, to be like the Lord? Or what difference then, between them and priuate? Sauing that they ſhal be worſe, by how much in place and power they are aduanced aboue others. Yea two ſuch they are, as in the vertue and ſtrength whereof, God bleſſeth among the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons euerie eſtate and condition, as well of peace, as of warre. For what is peace I ſay, and what is warre (ſpecially thorow mens corruption) without iuſtice? Peace is nothing els but carnall ſecuritie, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6835:13"/>warre nothing els but contention and theeuerie. Yea Iuſtice it ſelfe, thorow ſtrong and ſtrange paſſion, that ouerru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs all, paſſeth many times into his contrarie, that is to ſay, iniuſtice and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, vnleſſe we labor to make a good temperature, and intermingle much mercie therewithall. And this is the cauſe alſo why theſe two vertues are (as I may ſay) eſſentiall to all princes and magiſtrates, whereas the reſt tending to no other purpoſe, but as it were to ſerue theſe two, may bee called, and are in a manner accidentall. Which that wee may bee the better perſuaded of, let vs marke, that howſoeuer kings and ſtates liuing without war, and by conſequent, without acts of proweſſe and valiant deeds, may by meanes thereof bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, and be indeed much more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie than their neighbours, that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally combate and fight one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Yet herein is not the felicitie, either of the publike, or of the priuate condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but that it ſtandeth rather in this, that Iuſtice beareth ſway, and Mercie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6835:13"/>alſo is adminiſtred. For what are kings and ſtates without iuſtice and without mercie; without puniſhment, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out recompence,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
                  <hi>For terror to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and for honor to the good?</hi> What are they I ſay, but either ſo many ſcar crows, or ſo many Tyrants? And it hath neuer been ſeene, that ſtates haue ben wel gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and realmes rightly ruled, at the leaſt without ſome apparance and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of theſe qualities in them. The reaſon whereof is this, States con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in their ſubiects: for as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The glory of a king, is the multitude of his people:</hi> and ſubiects in ſocietie &amp; fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with another: &amp; Iuſtice is the onely band of all ſocietie amongſt men, which if it decay once, and bee not rightly executed, what can me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> look for, but all confuſion, diſorder, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and all other violence and outrage beſides? And hereof we may adde yet a further reaſon, Becauſe kings ſubſiſt by the loue of their people, and Mercie ſweeteneth and maketh eaſie vnto them that hard burden of their ſubiection.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6835:14"/>And therfore Mercie alſo is not without cauſe well called by one, <hi>The preſeruer of ſcepters.</hi> Yea I ſay, it ſeaſoneth this great power, otherwiſe intollerable to men, (for who would willingly be in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?) and otherwiſe alſo vnſupportable to it ſelfe; becauſe it is the eaſieſt thing of a thouſand, to turne lawfull authoritie into cruell oppreſſion and tyrannie.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that teach, profeſſe, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe Phyſike, begin after this manner: Firſt they propound the knowledge of mans bodie, afterwards followeth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of diet, either to vphold it in good ſtate, or to bring it to it, if it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied: yron and fire, that is to ſay, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off, and ſearing; come in the laſt place, being of accidents become ſuch inſtruments, as inconueniences thorow noiſome and feſtering diſeaſes, haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioined to that art, and mans intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie and corruption haue made ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie. And euen ſuch courſe as this muſt Magiſtrates obſerue in their poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike bodies, and in the ſickeneſſes and fores that ſprout and ſpread therein: not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6835:14"/>vſing corroſiues, but when the diſeaſe calleth for them: nor lenitiues, when biting plaiſters and medicines are meet. Adde hereunto, that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo well gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as hee was, knew well ynough, that kings raigne not by their armes, but by their heads; not by ſtrength only (much leſſe by violence) but by vertue: yea hee knew this further, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God ſhould call them to an account, concerning their offices and charges, hee would not ſay vnto them, You haue not beene bold ynough, valiant ynough, &amp;c. for men are naturally prone to ſuch things, and when they haue authoritie on their ſides, many times exceed therein: but this rather will he charge them withall, euen as this great king himſelfe telleth vs, <hi>Ye haue not iudged rightly. Ye that were,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.2.3. Wiſ. 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>or ſhould haue ben officers of my kingdome, ye haue not miniſtred mercy to the afflicted, the poore, and the widdow.</hi> The common people thinke theſe two vertues, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one of them to the other. But what a conceit is that? For if they were ſo, they could not bee in God, becauſe the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6835:15"/>Godhead being but one, and alwaies like it ſelfe, cannot admit contraries. And if that were true, how could it bee ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.10.</note> That <hi>all his waies are mercy &amp; truth, and all his workes mercie and iuſtice?</hi> And the like may bee in kings, or elſe how could they be called <hi>Fathers and Iudges.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 16.12.</note> And God himſelf hath ſaid in one place, <hi>The throne is eſtabliſhed by Iuſtice.</hi> And in another place he ſayth againe, <hi>The king vpholdeth his throne by Mercie.</hi> And as much is ſpoken doubtleſſe of all other men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 112.5.</note> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>The iuſt are mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 14.22.</note> 
                  <hi>and that their mercies are iuſtice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</hi> Againe, if that were ſo, to wit, that they were contraries, they could not themſelues be vertues, but the one or the other of them ſhould bee a vice; the reaſon whereof is plaine, becauſe no vertue is contrarie to vertue, but onely oppoſite to vice. And therefore if they were contraries, one of them, chuſe which you will, muſt needs bee a vice. Wherefore wee may ſafely conclude, that ſeeing they are not contraries, they doe not deſtroy one another, but rather
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6835:15"/>inſtruct and helpe one another: neither doe they driue away the one the other, but follow and accompanie the one the other, as thoſe that are in one and the ſelfe ſame God, and as it were going arme in arme together, tend to the ſame end. So that here that is verified, which the Prophet promiſed:<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Mercie and truth ſhall meet, righteouſneſſe and peace ſhal kiſſe one another.</hi> In God verily theſe great graces flow, from that verie eternall fountaine, which in him wee call good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which he communicateth to ſome after one maner &amp; meaſure, &amp; to others after another, according to his owne good pleaſure. And theſe graces, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diuers ſubiects wherein they are, and about which they are oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied, haue diners names. Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vpon or towards his owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is called Clemencie, Beniguitie, Mercie: but vpon, or towards the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, it changeth his name, and is tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Seueritie, Iudgement, and Iuſtice, Both the one and the other are good, and that not onelie as they come from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6835:16"/>God, but euen whether they tend, to bleſſing or to puniſhment. Good they are I ſay, for the aduancement of Gods glorie, and the vpholding of order in the world: for take away Mercie and Iuſtice and what ſhall we ſee amongſt men, but hell as it were let loſe? Good I ſay again for the ſocietie and fellowſhip of men, which without theſe two exerciſed and executed amongſt them, can neuer bee vpheld. And laſtly they are good, euen for them alſo to whome they are dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and vpon whome they are beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as who without theſe cannot either well or comfortablie paſſe the daies of their pilgrimage, or bee thorowly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. For as in reſpect of the godly, what conſolation is this, to know, that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie iuſtice of God is in them, &amp; for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Mercie and goodneſſe, that ſo his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe might bee exceeding great and large? And what a terror is this to the wicked, or at the leaſt wiſe ought it to be vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that Gods iuſtice &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall bee ſo much the more great and greeuous, by how much they haue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6835:16"/>fruit trampled and trodden vnderfoot his great grace and goodneſſe. Some are prouoked by bleſſings to ſerue the Lord. Others are moued to diſpleaſe and offend him euen by their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. In both God worketh, and for both prouideth by theſe meanes. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the eternall God himſelf, and then we ſhall ſee that his mercies are iuſtices, and his iuſtices are mercies. Will you ſee it by example? His iuſtice vpon Adam, was infinite mercie, as may well appeare by this, that being at the verie brinke of the bottomeleſſe pit, and hee might iuſtly haue thruſt him into the ſame, he withheld him notwithſtanding from it, and which is more, euen then <hi>gaue to him and his, his owne ſonne</hi> to ſaue them from death. And yet this infinite Mercie was as a man may ſay, ſwallowed vp of iuſtice, when he laid the ſinnes of men vpon the backe &amp; bodie of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſonne (I mean his whole perſon, yet without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founding of the properties of either nature) and was pleaſe, that in his only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all our debts ſhould
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6835:17"/>be exactly paid, and all our iniquities fullie pardoned.</p>
               <p>This point is meet for all eſtates and degrees to remember, as being full of heauenly comfort and ſpiritual inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but cheefely profitable for princes and great perſonages, who are Gods owne liuely images in this world, and therefore ſhould moſt remember and reſemble theſe things. True it is, that they cannot balance or beare them in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, or weigh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out to others ſo rightly as God doth, for they are imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect when they are at the beſt, and God is alwaies perfect and iuſt. And yet they ſhould beware of this, how they ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at warre, or make them to iarre one of them with another, or oppoſe them one of them againſt another. They ſhould rather on the other ſide perſuade themſelues of this, that that is indeed the moſt true Mercie, that keepeth in it ſelfe, and miniſtreth vnto others moſt of iuſtice: and that that is the moſt true Iuſtice, that holdeth in it ſelfe, and yet expreſſeth to others moſt of Mercie.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6835:17"/>So doe Mercie and Iuſtice in a prince, or vnder a prince, open the eyes &amp; cleer the ſight, as I may ſay, one of another. Mercie, whileſt it rightly ruleth the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and haughtineſſe of Iuſtice, which becauſe rulers many times inforce and conſtraine it further than is meet, may eaſily run riot, and be turned into rage: And Iuſtice, whileſt it moderateth the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that enlarge mercie too much, becauſe they are they that blind it, and cauſe it ſundrie times to fall vpon the wicked; it I ſay, euen that mercie I mean, which was borne and bred for the good onely: as on the other ſide, it cauſeth that rigour to light vpon good men, which was created &amp; made for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked alone. <hi>Dauid</hi> therefore here ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and ſetteth out vnto vs, both the one, and the other. He maketh them for our ſakes to accord well vpon his harpe, and bringeth both the one and the other to his proper and peculiar tune, them I ſay, which in truth tend both to one end, that is, the glorie of God, and the good of men, and bring forth the like
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6835:18"/>effect, to wit, faithfull obedience to Gods will.<note place="margin">Prou. 21.3.</note> For ſayth <hi>Salomon, Mercie and Iudgement are more acceptable to God, them ſacrifices.</hi> So that we may thence gather, that they make kings, as alſo al other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, acceptable before God. And in another place hee ſaith,<note place="margin">Prou. 21.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that purſueth Iuſtice and Mercie, ſhall find life and glorie.</hi> What meaneth he by this? Surely nothing els but this, that a good feeling, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full practiſe of theſe two holy vertues, will defend princes, and get them glorie in this world, and in the other, bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen to eternal life. But to find out theſe vertues, and to follow after them; euen the beſt, both men and Magiſtrats, haue need of a good guide. He onely that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this grace to kings, that they bee kings, muſt giue them alſo grace to raign aright, or to rule well. Wee ſay, no man is borne an artificer: much more ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may wee ſay, that no man is borne a goodking. For as it is one thing to bee borne a man, and another thing to bee a good man, ſo is it alſo to be born a king, and to bee a goodking. To God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6835:18"/>hee muſt come. And this <hi>Dauid</hi> did well ſee, when praying for himſelfe and his ſonne <hi>Salomon,</hi> hee ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 72.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>O God giue thy iudgements to the king, and thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſneſſe to the kings ſonne, to the end, that he may iuſtly gouerne thy people, and iudge the afflicted with equitie.</hi> And <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of himſelfe:<note place="margin">1. King. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.7.8.9.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord I know not how to goe out or in. Thy ſeruent is ſet ouer this great people: giue him an vnderstanding heart to iudge rightly, that he may diſcerne betweene good and euill: otherwiſe, who is able to gouerne this great people?</hi> Verie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and excellent doctrines are deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs out of theſe few words. Theſe vertues of which we haue ſpoken, haue their root and reſting place in goodnes, and indeed, cannot elſewhere be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And goodneſſe naturally communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and diſtributeth it ſelfe, as a grace that cannot containe it ſelfe within it ſelfe, but needs muſt breake forth for the glorie of him that giueth it, and the good of them who are partakers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Wherefore theſe royall and kingly vertues muſt ſend out their boughes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6835:19"/>and branches, euen vnto the borders of the kingdome and countrey, ſo as there may not be any, though neuer ſo mean, but in ſome meaſure more or leſſe, they ſhould partake thereof. One of them ſpreadeth out it ſelfe in the ſinewes, that ſo it may preſerue the people, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their dutie. The other ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out it ſelfe in the veines, comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to water the land, and the people thereof, with the Princes fauour. And this is that ſame common and generall good which the Prince oweth vnto all his ſubiects, Iuſtice I meane, and with it, peace and protection, or defence alſo, and that without difference or reſpect, be herein framing &amp; conforming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto God, the ſoueraigne Lord, <hi>Who maketh his ſunne to ſhine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.45.</note> 
                  <hi>and his rain to fall indifferently vpon the good and the euill,</hi> giuing more ſometimes to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed and afflicted, than to others that are not humbled, not only becauſe they ſtand in more need, but alſo becauſe Mercie in his own nature, draweth nigh vnto him that hath need thereof as Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6835:19"/>likewiſe to him that lieth more open to outrage and violence: he follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing herein that which is commanded, <hi>Open thy mouth for the dumbe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 31.8.</note> 
                  <hi>in the cauſe and right of them that are appointed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction:</hi> and herein alſo faſhioning himſelfe like vnto God,<note place="margin">Pro. 23.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Who boweth down his head to heare him that is humbled, &amp; keepeth himſelf continually about them that are by an afflicted ſpirit, and watcheth ouer the harneſt of the fatherleſse, and preſerueth the widdowes bounds.</hi> But to them that are knowne for good people, and found in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to bee men of godlineſſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie, there is another mercie, there is another iuſtice due, that is, to ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them Chriſtian countenance, and particular or ſpeciall fauour, to cheriſh them, to acknowledge them for ſuch, &amp; to honour in them that grace or graces, which God hath vouchſafed vnto them to honour him withall: that ſo he might apparently diſtinguiſh them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others, that indeed are not ſuch. Euerie one ſhould learn to put a difference betwixt <hi>the precious and the vile,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and to make
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6835:20"/>much of them that feare the Lord.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the prince much more ſhould doe it, becauſe he ſhould be of a more diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit than other men, and it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> peece of his dutie to obſerue and make this difference. And yet wee many times ſee, that none are more blind than they, and none leſſe regarded; or rather more contemned than thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tly feare God: It may be we know not what it is to honour them. If that be ſo, let vs liſten and learne a little. To honor good men is nothing elſe but to ſound; yea &amp; if need be, to ſend them abroad into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> world; and by that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nes to ſtir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vp at deſire in all, both to reſemble them, and indeed to become ſuch. But to leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrapped vp in confuſion, and in a maſſe of miſerie, that is nothing elſe but to make vice and vertue all one, or rather indeed, againſt vertue to ſtreng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vice: vice I ſay, which is but of too much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count amongſt men, yea which is but too much in euerie one of vs, by reaſon of the ſecret intelligences, which it hath with our corrupted nature. And ſo by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6835:20"/>this wee ſee ſecond ſtep of Gods goodneſſe towards men, which as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in this, that he maketh them his children, his deerelie beloued oues; his heires, and reſerueth for them his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and diſtributeth freely his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vnto them: ſo doth it more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly appeare, as in reſpect of kings, who though by nature they may be borne to kingdomes, or by men be choſen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, yet neuer can haue grace to be kings indeed, but from him,<note place="margin">I am. 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>From whom alone deſcendeth euery good gift, &amp; perfect grace:</hi> and who can neuer faile them indeed, or euer will, except it bee through iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, neglect of dutie, or other ſome grecuous tranſgreſſion, ſeeing it hath pleaſed the ſoueraigne Lord to make them ſuch to himſelfe and his ſeruants: And from this ſecond degree or ſtep, we come vnto the third, that is, that amongſt theſe good people, thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed with ſome ſpeciall grace for the managing of ſome ſpecial affaires, and for al other good purpoſes, Iuſtice would, that euen the verie mercy
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:6835:21"/>his owne father. Here Mercie will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine; and that euen as if it were in the aire, and before it come to ſtrike, the ſword of Iuſtice, which otherwiſe is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry readie to execute that ſame ſeuere and hard decree, <hi>He that killeth, ſhall die the death.</hi> In laws (no more than in other formes of ſpeech) men are not ſo much to regard the words thereof, as the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and end of the ſame, becauſe many times the words may bee much more hard than the meaning. A certain yong woman of Roman goeth, and with her own breſt noriſheth hir father in priſon, an yet the arreſt and decree that was pronounced againſt him meant, that he ſhuld die there by famine. Mercie in this proceſſe againſt law, did right to nature, and turned that rigor into grace, &amp; that crime into vertue &amp; praiſe. So that euen here the Apoſtles ſpeech is true,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Mercie r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ioiceth agaiſt condemnation or iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Likewiſe, by Gods law it was not permitted to any but to the prieſts, to eat the ſhew bread And by the ſame law men are alſo ſtraitly commanded to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6835:21"/>obſerue and fanctifie the Sabboth. But yet when the queſtion is, to nouriſh and feed one ſore bitten with hunger, as for example, <hi>Dauid Gods annointed,</hi> who was vniuſtly baniſhed from <hi>Saules</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: or elſe to comfort a mans neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in extremitie, or to defend his countrey, &amp;c. the caſe will quickely bee altered, and the ſtare of the queſtion ſoone changed. And here once againe Mercie taketh vpon it the cauſe of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, againſt the letter of the law. Yea here the very authour of Mercie and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice telleth vs, that the law muſt giue place to charitie (<hi>which indeed is the true butt &amp; end of the law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.5. Roma. 13.8.</note> 
                  <hi>yea the very fulfilling of it, as the Apoſtle ſaith</hi>) yea that our neighbour in this caſe muſt be preferred before the verie Sabboth it ſelfe. Which if it bee true in a priuat and particular perſon, will much more bee ſtrong in an extreame danger or neceſſitie of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſtate, which ought to be ſo much the more regarded, by how much maine, yea all, are to bee preferred before one, or ſome. But perhaps it will ſeeme to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6835:22"/>ſundrie that wee doe not farre ynough inlarge the skirts and bounds of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, becauſe wee make it the interpreter of Iuſtice, and ſome would, that wee ſhould make it a part thereof. Whervp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo it may bee, they will ſay vnto vs: what? ſhall not the king ſhew fauours? Otherſome perhaps will ſay againe: ſhall not the king lift vp and aduance, or create (as ſome vſe to ſay) ſuch as hee ſhall like of? But wee anſwere, that wee are ſo farre off from diſliking his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that if hee will follow our counſell, he ſall doe nothing but ſhew fauours, yea true fauours indeed, for they ſhall be ciuile, and ſuch as ſauour of Iuſtice and Mercie together. Howbeit, vnder the colour or ſhaddow of Mercie and Iuſtice, the king wee meane and ſpeake of, ſhall not commit iniuſtice. For Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and Iuſtice to, ſhall neuer ſerue him in ſteed of a maske or viſar, neither ſhall they euer lend him their glorious appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell to ſo bad a purpoſe, and wicked end, as to couer iniquitie. If hee bee ſuch a Prince as he ought to be, he will not for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6835:22"/>ſome tenderneſſe of heart in himſelfe, or towards others, much leſſe at the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of a courtier will he winke at a heinous crime, and make it no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: as for example, a deſperate mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or a ſlaughter committed, with thought of it beforehand, or a rape, &amp;c. but as hee will liſten vnto the wife and friend of the offending partie, ſo he will heare the crie of the fatherleſſe, hee will ſet before his eyes the teares of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and in thinking vpon the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſorrow of ſome, hee will weigh the publike hurt and domage, which no doubt of it cannot but bee increaſed, by the letting of ſinne go vnpuniſhed, and that that may inſue thereupon. The truth of this is confirmed by that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſpeech of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Prou. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.15.</note> 
                  <hi>He that iuſtifieth the wicked</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>and he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the righteous, they are both an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination to the Lord.</hi> And if a man would ſee it watranted, let him regard but the ſentence of God himſelfe <hi>(who is no reſpecter of perſons)</hi> and that pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and giuen againſt a king, truly clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6835:23"/>with the purble or ſcarlet robe, and then he ſhall heare a verie fearefull one:<note place="margin">2. Kin. 20.42.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe thou haſt ſaued him</hi> (ſaith the eternall God) <hi>whom I appointed to die, they life ſhall be for his life, and thy people for his people.</hi> Wherefore where God ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, the Princes heart, hand, or e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, muſt not ſpare: and as God appointeth, ſo muſt he execute, both for ſoundneſſe of ſentence, vprightneſſe of affection, end of puniſhment and all, or elſe it is not aright.</p>
               <p>Princes paraſites pretend many pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges for them, as abolitions procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from fulneſſe of power, matters of merry motion, and ſundrie ſuch like, as wee call them reſerued caſes, all which the ſoueraigne king holdeth in his owne hands, neither transferreth them to any perſon whatſoeuer. Howbeit here it were good for them to conſider what they ſuppoſe, heold, or practiſe in ſuch caſes. For though wee will not impaire, no not in the leaſt iot, any part of kingly dignitie, yet this we cannot diſſemble, that to vſe them, is to attempt againſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6835:23"/>God, to wound his Maieſtie, to violate his Iuſtice, and to vſurpe vpon his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Hee himſelfe being incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mercie, and infinite power, when he purpoſed to aboliſh ſinne, hath not ſo vſed to ſpeake. Doe wee not ſee that it was his good pleaſure, and hee determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it with himſelfe, and in time accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed it, that in his onely begotten ſon (a wonderfull ſecret of his grace) his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhould bee ſatisfied? That is to ſay, to ſpeake properly, that his Mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, became Iuſtice. Little or no fauour at all ſhall a Prince beſtow, nay rather he ſhall commit a great and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous euill, when vnder the ſhaddow and colour of Mercie, hee ſhall raiſe vp to one or ſundrie dignities, an vnworthie perſon, and ſhall create for Magiſtrates ſuch as are incapable and vnmeet for the ſame. This word, to create, properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth to raiſe vp, or make of nothing. And flatterers would make Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that herein they draw nigh to the greatneſſe, and to goodneſſe of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, that they haue their crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6835:24"/>And that they might the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force, it they ſay, that the leſſe a man hath in himſelfe to bee placed in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, this ſhall be the more euident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration and apparent act of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power, to ſet them very high. But fie vpon ſuch prophane propoſitions, and farre bee it from any Chriſtian heart to delight in, or dare to heare ſuch blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous voices: for to create, is an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable proprietie of God, neuer to be giuen to all or any of the creatures, to men or to kings. God himſelfe, the onely law and ruler of all things, that he might the better ſet out vnto kings the examples of his grace, neuer vſeth it but iuſtly, and in matters of great goodnes. And ſhall princes applie it to purpoſes and practiſes of inconueniences and ſinne? God of a lumpe of clay createth a man. In confeſſe that to bee true, but hee leaueth not there, hee proceedeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and breatheth into him the ſpirit of iudgement, and of life, yea he putteth into him all that which is meet for the making of a man. Who can forbid him
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6835:24"/>from a cottage or ſheepefold, to take a Prince for himſelfe and his people (<hi>as he did Dauid</hi>) ſeeing hee giueth him his ſpirit to conduct him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.70.</note> and hee powreth aboundantly vpon his head all that is needfull for him to make him a Prince. In this reſpect is it, that verie beaſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues diſdaine not to obey man, neither doe men ſo refuſe to honour their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But kings verily, when they make men of no worth, Magiſtrates, they giue them, yea they can giue them no more, but the name: yea they doe leſſe for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than a painter doth for the image that he hath portraited, for hee can alter and change it at his pleaſure, and make it and deface it, as ſeemeth good to himſelfe: but they change not either the qualitie or the ſubſtance, they cannot alter his head, nay they cannot adde or diminiſh an haire. And many times they ſet them ſo high, that they are readie at leaſtwiſe in affection, to ſet them beſides the ſeat. All which ſhould worke lowlineſſe in worldlie gouernours, and ſhould make them warie whom they aduance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:6835:25"/>
But our Prophet proceedeth &amp; ſaith: <hi>O Lord I will ſing them vnto thee.</hi> He ſaith not, I will ſing them vnto men: neither ſaith he, that he will exerciſe Iuſtice and Mercie to pleaſe them. And doubtleſſe as little regard will hee haue, of feare to diſpleaſe them, but would reſpect the Lord onely,<note place="margin">Acts. 17.23.</note> becauſe <hi>he did liue and raign by him,</hi> to him,<note place="margin">Prou. 8.15.</note> and for him: by him, as in reſpect of his power; to him, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the rules he had ſet him; and for him, as in conſideration of the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his praiſe. Good reaſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhould doe theſe things to him, for verily, Iuſtice and Mercie that are practiſed by occaſion of men, or for hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reſpects, are flacteries, hypocriſies, idolatries: flatteries, becauſe they are done to pleaſe men; hypocriſies, becauſe they make a better ſhew than they are; and idolatries, becauſe they rob God of his glorie, and cauſe men to fall downe before men. But concerning them in things of a like nature, the Lord hath ſaid,<note place="margin">Math. 6.2.</note> 
                  <hi>They haue their reward,</hi> that is, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, honour, &amp; ceremonies from men,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6835:25"/>becauſe they are done to men. But the Iuſtice and Mercie, that haue God for their obiect, and are referred to his glor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſet him before them, who is the beholder of actions, <hi>and the ſearches of hearts,</hi> they I ſay, haue him <hi>for a rewarder</hi> and recompence of them,<note place="margin">1. Co. 10.13. Rom. 8.32. Pſal. 16.11.</note> that is <hi>faithful. And hauing him, how can they not but toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him haue all things alſo, becauſe in his preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy, and at his right hand there are pleaſures for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> And this is it that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth: <hi>They haue for their wages and hire of well doing, both glorie and life.</hi> Againe, it many times falleth out, that the Prince cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a wicked inſtrument or perſon to be executed. The deed is good, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps hee is moued thereto, rather with courage and ſtoutneſſe of heart in himſelfe, than with the vileneſſe or dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the deed. This worke I ſay is iuſt in it ſelfe, for the malefactor by his ſinne deſerued the puniſhment, yet hee that doth it, is notwithſtanding vniuſt. Nay, I will ſay more than ſo: Reſpect him and the wicked affection of his heart,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6835:26"/>and then I cannot but ſay, hee is a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, and that not onely when with a hatefull heart hee cauſeth a guiltie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to bee executed, but when hee hath appointed or commanded his innocent neighbour to bee ſlaine. On the other ſide, a Prince powreth out his fauor vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a fit perſon. The action is good, and the man it may bee deſerued all that is beſtowed vpon him. Howbeit, hee that did it, was happily moued with ſome blameworthie affection, as he reſpected kindred onely, or conſidered fauour, or did dread ſome feare, or had ſome ſuch worldlie regard or other. But here nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the man that did it, nor the deed it ſelfe, as in reſpect of him, is to bee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And why? becauſe it aimed neither at religious reſpects, nor right ends: &amp; ſo by that meanes his Mercie becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth corruption, and his vertue ſhall be vnto him, as if it were a vice. So much doth vertue deſire to bee cheriſhed for her owne ſake, or rather ſo much is God (the very fountaine of all vertue) iealous of his honour, and iealous alſo of our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6835:26"/>loue, that he will haue euery good thing (to the end it may be good indeed) to be referred vnto himſelfe, and to the ends that he hath appointed, as indeed all is taken, and commeth from him alone, and therefore alſo ſhould bee referred vnto him and his glorie onely, as the Apoſtle plainly ſheweth, when he ſaith: <hi>Whether you eat or drinke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31.</note> 
                  <hi>or whatſoeuer els you doe, doe all to the glorie of God.</hi> To bee ſhort, the Prince ſhould properly both referre and approue his actions to God, ſeeing that God alone, and not man hath ſet him vp, and ſeeing that hee is not to bee iudged by men, and ſeeing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that in the power, by which hee is eſtabliſhed, he hath none for his Iudge but God alone. Wherfore it is truly ſaid by the wiſe man, <hi>That where the kings word is, there is power:</hi> none can demand a reckoning of him for that which he doth. And yet notwithſtanding he ſayth alſo in another place,<note place="margin">Iohn. 19.11. Wiſd. 6.3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>That this power is giuen him by the almightie, whoſe miniſter or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer hee is, who alſo will make inquirie tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his life, and will ſound euen to his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6835:27"/>very thoughts.</hi> By all which wee may ſee, that though Kings and Princes bee ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme among men, yet they may not liue as they liſt,<note place="margin">Pſalme 82.</note> 
                  <hi>But muſt die as other men,</hi> and afterwards, as the reſt of the people, render an account to God of all things done in the fleſh. To conclude this point withall. Great and excellent things as we may ſee, are comprehended vnder theſe two tearmes, <hi>Mercie</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:</hi> which are indeed the very abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſumme of all that kings ſhould learne and doe. And ſeeing that they are of ſo deeper a reach, and extend ſo farre as they doe, wee may thereby plainely perceiue, that it is no light care and charge to bee a king, neither is it an art or trade caſily learned, to rule well. And that is the reaſon alſo why in the words following, <hi>Dauid</hi> telleth vs:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 2.</hi> I will attend vnto the perfect way, vntill that thou commeſt to me: In the vprightnes of my heart; I will walke in the middeſt of my houſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:6835:27"/>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Auid</hi> in his former words had made a vow touching Mercie and Iuſtice. The things are good that all men will confeſſe: but yet we are ſure it is no eaſie matter to bring them to execution, ſpecially for him that is not mercifull and iuſt. And that cauſeth the Prophet now to ſay, that hee will ſtudie and endeuour to bee ſuch a one. His meaning in them words is, that he could not become a good Prince, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he did firſt begin to be a good man, rightly ruling his owne perſon, and his priuate life, that ſo hauing made proofe of them in that calling, he might be the better aſſured of the practiſe of them, when he ſhould come into publike. This leſſon and doctrine in quite and cleane contrarie to the courts and courſes of our age. And what better proofe can we haue of it, than mens deeds and words. As for their deeds, they are too appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and as for their ſpeeches they haue paſſed this as a cuſtomary and ordinary point, yea they haue made it a prouerb,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6835:28"/>or by-word, as we ſay, of an il man a good Prince. Why doe not they approue of this, A ſhrewd boy, a good man, if that be true? And why doe they not bring vp their youths in all diſſolution and naughtineſſe? But Gods truth teacheth vs otherwiſe: for it is the feare of God that maketh a good man, and is indeed the beginning of a Prince. Whereof we may yet bee the better perſuaded, ſith <hi>Princes</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>raigne by wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 8.15.</note> and ſith alſo, that euen of that wiſedome <hi>the feare of God is the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 9.10.</note> that is to ſay, the beginning of a vertuous and wiſe Prince. The Prince certainely by his office is the guide of his ſubiects. He muſt then either know the way himſelfe, or at leaſtwiſe learne it; or elſe how can hee be able to direct and guide others? He is an example for them to frame their manners by, and therefore vnleſſe he can frame his owne well, he ſhall doe them ſmall good. But ſaith the ſame wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 14.12.</note> 
                  <hi>There is a way that ſeemeth right vnto a man, but the iſſue thereof tendeth to death.</hi> The Prince
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6835:28"/>therefore, both as in regard of himſelfe, and as in reſpect of his ſubiects alſo, hath great need to take heed thereto, and the rather becauſe by many auocaments, as if it were by by-paths, he may more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be turned aſide than others. And that cauſeth <hi>Salomon</hi> in another place to ſay: <hi>The way of a folle is right in his owne eyes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 12.15.</note> by which alſo he would giue vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that it is not his owne opinion or iudgement, that hee muſt beleeue, and much leſſe muſt he ſticke to the opinion of other men, ſeeing that all men are nothing els but obſcurity, yea the world it ſelfe is very darkeneſſe. In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard we may ſay, that our ſteps are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but ſo many ſtumblings, yea ſo many fals. And yet notwithſtanding, they are our ſteps ſtill, yea ſuch as God weigheth well, and examineth rightlie, <hi>yea ſuch as the Lord hath alwaies before his eyes.</hi> Wherefore certainely,<note place="margin">Prou. 5.21.</note> if other men had need, much more the king muſt ſay with <hi>Dauid, O Lord cauſe mee to know thy waies, euen thy commandements, to the end, that mine eyes may ſee them. Let
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6835:29"/>thy word be a lanterne vnto my feet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 19.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and a light vnto my path:</hi> yea to pray as hee doth in another place.<note place="margin">Pſ. 119. 105. Pſ. 119.133.</note> 
                  <hi>Stay my feet in thy word, and guide thou my ſteps, and ſuffer not any iniquitie to haue dominion ouer mee.</hi> Light of nature, good intents in our ſelues, other mens aduiſe or example, will not ſerue here. For neither are the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the way, neither will they ſteed vs to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs therein. No, Gods law only is this way:<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.</note> that way (ſaith hee) <hi>which reſtoreth the ſoule, which giueth wiſdome to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> this was the way that made him, euen then when hee as but a Sheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, <hi>to vnderſtand more than all the aged,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119 99.100.</note> 
                  <hi>and to be indeed more wiſe than thoſe that had taught him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119.24.</note> Yea (ſaith he) <hi>Thy te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies are my pleaſures or paſtimes, thy ſtatutes are my counſellors:</hi> meaning by that manner of ſpeech, that be thought, ſaid, or did nothing, but he aduiſed with the Word, firſt. So much ſtudied hee in this booke of the Law, that God had graciouſly giuen for inſtruction to him and all other Princes. And herein hee did the rather and the more diligently
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6835:29"/>imploy and buſie himſelfe, becauſe God had commanded him, and ſuch as hee was,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.18.19.</note> 
                  <hi>That after hee ſhould bee ſet vpon the throne of his kingdome, he ſhould write out a copie of his law into a booke, to the end, ſaith hee, that hee might learne to feare the Lord his God, to execute his law, and not to lift vp himſelfe in pride aboue his brethren,</hi> that ſo the feare of God might hold him in his dutie, and within the bounds of Mercie and Iuſtice, without declining therefrom either to the right hand, or to the left: without which hee could not but goe aſide, either to the one hand, or to the other. To the left, as they doe which make an occupation of rigor and roughneſſe, that ſo vnder the pretext of auſteritie, they may obtaine with the hurt and loſſe of ſome poore and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable people, the reputation and credit to be good Iuſtices. Concerning whom <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be not ye iuſt ouer much.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccle. 7.18.</note> For who art thou O man, that wilt rule the balance more right and ſtreit than God? God I ſay, <hi>Who hath made all things in weight, number, and meaſure.</hi> To the right
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6835:30"/>hand as they doe, who vnder the pretext of pitie, will with the hurt and hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Iuſtice, play the merciful men: of whom the ſame <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth: <hi>Many men will boaſt, euery man of his own goodnes and mercie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 20, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>but where ſhal one find a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man?</hi> But who art thou alſo O man, that vndertakeſt to bee more mercifull, fauourable and gentle than God? God I ſay, that is an infinite fountain of mercy. God I ſay, who of that infinit mercie of his only, hath made thee, hath maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thee, and ſuſtaineth and noriſheth thee, in whom &amp; by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone thou art and muſt be iuſt and merciful, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom, if thou ſuppoſe thy ſelfe to haue Iuſtice, it is but iniurie, and if thou take thy ſelfe to haue mercie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, it is but hard heartedneſſe and Tyrannie.</p>
               <p>Neither muſt mans wiſedome here glorifie or lift vp it ſelfe againſt this of Gods, as though it vnderſtood ſome further ſecret, myſterie or matter, in or about theſe gracious qualities. <hi>Kings raigne by God,</hi> and therefore they muſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6835:30"/>be directed by him, yea they ſhall beſt and longeſt raigne, that ſerue him beſt and moſt. Now ſerue him they cannot, but according to his will: and his will is not knowne to vs, but by his Word and Law. They proſper through his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>and his bleſsing is vpon them that fear him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 1.50.</note> We will ſay a little more than this. The moſt aſſured art and skill by which men may raigne well and long, is the feare of God in their hearts, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie and vprightneſſe in themſelues. Which that we might be the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded of,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30.</note> God telleth vs <hi>that be will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them that honour him.</hi> The onely ſhaddow of theſe qualities made the Heathen to rule wel and to raigne long. Then what will the effect and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance doe? And if for counterfeiting of them (as indeed the Heathen had no more but the very picture of them, if they had ſo much) the Pagans were yet notwithſtanding beloued and feared of their ſubiects, who can or will doubt then, but that a good, a godly, and a vertuous Prince, obtaining them from
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6835:31"/>God in himſelfe, and poſſeſſing them and expreſſing them to the people, ſhall be reuerenced of his owne for them, and admired at of others, abroad, when hee doth accompliſh and performe them. <hi>Wherefore I will ſtudie ſaith he, this leſſon, waiting till thou come O Lord, and draw nigh vnto me,</hi> making mee quiet and peaceable in my kingdome, that ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with full authoritie, and a good meaſure of graces from thee, I may find my ſelfe fit therefore. Yea to this end al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo will I ſtudie, read, heare, and learne, that thy bleſſing being begun in mee, by this meanes may increaſe vpon mee, as thy feare alſo in me, that ſo thou O Lord God (who art the beginning, middeſt, &amp; end of all things, and haſt beſtowed this fauour vpon me to be a king) maieſt alſo giue me grace to raigne, yea aboue all things to be a good king, and to rule and raigne holilie. And in the ſelfe ſame ſteps and trace, muſt all good kings tread, or els it will neuer bee well with them. For if they thinke vpon other mens bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, or weigh weakeneſſe in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6835:31"/>or take of trouble, paſt, preſent, or to come, a thouſand to one but they will goe awrie. Of a truth <hi>Dauid</hi> after that he was annointed, was not without his troubles and trials. The holy hiſtory ſheweth, that he had both the Philiſtims and Iſraelites againſt him, ſtraungers abroad, and them of his owne people and houſe at home. Yet hee was not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged for all that, but hee waited vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and looked for the accompliſhment of Gods promiſes, and expected the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time and houre that God hat ſet, trauelling notwithſtanding continually in the duties of his calling, and aboue all things being carefull for, yea as I may ſay, curious about the glorie of God. And why hath God in the word, and in the world, ſet forth his owne and others examples? Is it not by them as it were to prouoke to well doing? To a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an king, this is a great fauour of God, to be borne a king, and to be lawfully deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to the crowne, and to weare and enioy the ſame. But who maketh vſe of theſe mercies? If a man come not to it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6835:32"/>when he would, and as he would, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to doubt of Gods grace, and falleth to ſhifting: whereas he ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtedfaſtly to aſſure himſelfe, that he ſhall come to it in good time, euen in that time which God hath appointed: who being the protectour of kings and princes, of lawes and lands, will neuer faile the one or the other, if they ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly depend on him. Againe, if they be once in poſſeſſion of it, who <hi>abuſeth not Gods mercy, and turneth his, grace into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſse,</hi> and their lawfull authoritie into Tyrannie? So hard a matter is it to keep a meane, and to tarrie the Lords leiſure. And whereas God, the better to haſten Princes on to their due, and to ſettle them more faſt in their kingdomes, will haue them to call vpon him, and to walk in the obedience of his will: and the yeeld him, is to cauſe their ſubiects <hi>to call vpon him in ſpirit and truth.</hi> And for their better incouragement, hee hath promiſed them <hi>that he wil find them when they ſhall come vnto him,</hi> and manage his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6835:32"/>houſe well, and carefully watching ouer his familie, receiue a bleſſing in the end, with <hi>that good ſeruant</hi> in the Goſpell, <hi>whom his maiſter will make ruler ouer all his goods:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 24.47.</note> yet hardlie ſhall wee find any king prouoked by theſe good things, or diſcouraged by the contrary euils, from violating their places &amp; callings. Thoſe certainely that tee themſelues ſeated in their thrones, and without contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on acknowledged of their ſubiects, that they in the midſt of mans vanitie, ſhould ouerſhoot themſelues, and exceed their bounds, and thinke in their proſperitie they haue no need of God, it is not much to be maruelled at, becauſe they ſuppoſe they hold it from their aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and humane right. But hee, who in all euidencie of iudgement is become a ſoueraigne prince by Gods grace only, who by the hand hath drawne him from the depth of miſerie, and yet ſeeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at the pits brinke, but that God hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him from it, he I ſay, ought to haue another manner of motion, and another manner of pulſe, or elſe ſurely his ſtate
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:6835:33"/>the ſame hand that hath hurt and ſtriken for ſinne, might ſalue and heale for his owne mercies ſake. And as mean might is there in our plots, in our negotiations, in our treaties with other. For hee that<note place="margin">Prou. 16.7.</note> hath ſaid vnto vs, <hi>when a mans way plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God, his very enemies ſhall become his friends,</hi> hath by conſequent taught vs, that if the Princes waies diſpleaſe the Lord, that then hee is mightie ynough to harden them againſt him by ſundrie meanes, as warre by ſea and land, open hoſtilitie, priuate practiſes: and indeed powerfull to cauſe them that were friends and confederates, to reuolt and fall away from him, as bee did from <hi>Dauid his friends, his counſellours, yea his owne children,</hi> and that in the time of great peace and proſperitie, which no doubt of it, did and might increaſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iudgement and afflictions.</p>
               <p>And this is the cauſe why hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> earning, <hi>I will walke in the integritie or v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ght.</hi> Yea I <hi>of my heart,</hi> that is to ſay, I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſay, <hi>O how</hi> know the vpright way for ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>clare my loue do, &amp; be neuer a whit the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> meanes that hee
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:6835:33"/>God I ſay,<note place="margin">Pſ. 139.11.12.</note> becauſe <hi>darkeneſſe is light vnto him, and the night and the light to him are both alike.</hi> The people, becauſe my ſelfe ſhould ſtand them in ſteed of a light: yea the people I ſay againe, becauſe by the multitude of their eies, they pierce euen into the thickeſt of my cloſe and hidden places, yea euen into the bottome of the vices of their prince. And in reſpect of men I wil walke in this courſe, the rather to remoue ſurmiſes out of their minds, and obloquie and ill ſpeech out of their mouths, nothing being more ordinarie with them, than not onely with a cauſe, but without a cauſe to detract. And as in regard of God, I will the rather ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it, and doe it in deed, becauſe hee being the Lord of all (euen he whome I call vpon, and vpon whom I wait) will come and cal me to an account, and ſay, <hi>Well good ſeruant</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 19.17.</note> 
                  <hi>thou haſt ben faithfull in ſmall matters, take thou authority notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ouer tenne Cities.</hi> Thou haſt had skill, and ben able to gouerne thine own houſe, now take charge of mine. In this little authoritie and ſmall power in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6835:34"/>compariſon, that I committed into thy hand, thou haſt carried thy ſelfe as thou oughteſt, <hi>I will therefore eſtabliſh thy throne for euer, I will put thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vnder thy feet.</hi> This vow I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, is a very hard point for a Prince. Why, and ſo are all excellent things: And ſhall hee therefore neglect them? And they will bee ſo much the more hard, if his will be tempted with power, and his power be prouoked by libertie, and his libertie laſh out into licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: or if ſinne and euill come, and preſent it ſelf euen to confront him, and that after diuerſe manners, and vnder ſundrie maskes (as no doubt but it will) ſometimes amiable to allure, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ougly to terrirfie. But <hi>Dauid</hi> knew well how to diſcomfite and ouerthrow theſe crafts and deceits. And therefore he ſaith, as for the diſcharge of his owne conſcience, ſo for the inſtruction of all other, whom it may concerne:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:6835:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 3.</hi> I will ſet no wicked thing before mine eyes. I hate the workes of them that fall away, nothing thereof ſhall cleaue vnto me.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Auid</hi> heretofore, as wee haue heard, made a ſolemne vow to keepe his heart ſound and ſure vnto God. And good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſhould bee ſo, for if ſuch as haue a place to keepe, or a fort to looke vnto (to the end they may alwaies keepe the enemie far off) doe as well watch againſt afterclaps, as for feare of preſent perill. Shall not wee thinke that wee haue as great need to looke to, or watch ouer our heart? Yes verily. And therefore the Lord commandeth vs in his word, <hi>aboue all watchings to obſerue the heart.</hi> Which that wee may the better keepe, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle our hearts vnto God, we muſt know that it becommeth vs to keepe our eies, and indeed to ſtop our eares alſo. For vice hath great power and force againſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6835:35"/>men, yea it eaſily enſnareth them by the eare, thorow diſſolute words, and leaud and <hi>euill ſpeeches</hi> which corrupt good manners.<note place="margin">1. Co. 15.33.</note> And a great entrance hath vice alſo into our hearts, by occaſion of the windowes. For euen as when the enemie hath gained our centinels and watchtoures, our ouerthrow in all likely hood, is not farre off: ſo is it when pleaſure hath bewitched our eies, and ſinne thruſt it ſelfe, by the ſtrength and ſting of it, into our ſoules. Which wee may ſee to bee true euen in our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who were taken, yea ouertaken by the eare, by the onely whiſteling of that wicked and wilie ſerpent, who impoyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his ſweet and coloured ſpeeches, their hearts and their ſpirits, they being then notwithſtanding vpright, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled through creation, and as yet not ſubiect to appetites, nor worldly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, as we are ſince ſinne entred into the world. Oh then what may Sathan do now by our eares, againſt a, ſpirit that is ſenſuall, againſt a heart that is fleſhlie, againſt reaſon vanquiſhed by ſence, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6835:35"/>againſt a will, that ſauoureth of nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut carnal appetites? So we ſee, how <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was caught, <hi>and yet a man according to Gods own hart.</hi> He had no ſooner ſet open the window, but the theefe entered in thereat: vice I meane, that aſſaieth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but by offering a taſt, craftily to ſurpriſe vs indeed. And marke I pray you, how ſinne proceedeth in him: by the eies it ſurpriſed the heart, yea it ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and robbed him of his ſoule. Of a gracious king, and godlie Prophet, hee made him in a moment a wicked adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and moſt cruel murtherer. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all conſider the equitie of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. By the ſame window the Lord cauſeth him to ſee his fearefull wrath entring vpon him, and to behold the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away of his ſonne, the reuolting of his people, and ſundrie ſuch like, which are indeed the ordinarie companions of our diſorderous enormities. So mightie to euill, is our infirmitie, and our might and power to reſiſt it ſo weake. Doth not our owne obſeruation of others, and experience in our ſelues teach vs,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6835:36"/>that if the eye be once gained, our fort yeeldeth vp it ſelfe, it can no longer bee kept. Which the Prophet being well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, doth in one place pray, <hi>Turne away mine eies from regarding va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119.37.</note> as here alſo hee telleth vs, <hi>I will ſhut mine eare.</hi> And our Lord and Sauiour ſayth:<note place="margin">Math. 5.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Pull out the eie, if cauſe thee to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard or deſtroy thy ſoule.</hi> In ſteed whereof, the Princes of our age (that they may the better giue themſelues ouer to euill and ſinne, and ſo not bee ſeized with the miſcheefes that follow thereupon) moſt commonlie ſet open all their fiue wits and ſences as wee ſay, to pleaſures: but againſt paines, puniſhments, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, they ſhut their eies. Whereas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it were more fit for them, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold theſe, becauſe thereby they might preuent euil, be humbled in themſelues, and ſhew compaſſion to others: and to ſhut their ſight againſt the other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the more they looke vpon them, the more <hi>they draw iniquitie with the cords of vanitie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 5.18.</note> But wee are to ſee what it is, not to ſet our eies to behold euill.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6835:36"/>Surely it is to flie euill: it is to flie and auoid the occasions of euill, it is to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſinne at the very barre, and to keepe it as farre as may be from the gate, that ſo hauing no entrance, it may haue no preuailing. But hath it ſometimes gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and preuailed euen vpon the eye? Let vs not deſpaire for all that. God hath prouided for vs good meanes to cut it off, and to pull it out. Let vs looke to our weapons, and labour to vſe them, ſith God hath beene pleaſed to miniſter diuers vnto vs, againſt the fraud and the force of our eies. As for example, let vs ſtay our ſelues vpon, and defend our ſelues by our reaſon, againſt the aſſault of our appetites. Let vs oppoſe our ſelues againſt our will, being fortified by Gods word.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> Againſt <hi>this law of our members,</hi> let vs ſet the law of God, the force of the ſpirit, and the power of the ſoule. And then let vs not doubt, but that God will aſſiſt vs, that he will come and heale vs, yea that hee will helpe vs and claime vs for his owne, for ſo hath hee promiſed. And this is indeed the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6835:37"/>combat of a ſouldiour, yea of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an princes againſt pleaſures, againſt profits, againſt affections, and whatſoeuer elſe, becauſe as that is true that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Pro. 16.32.</note> 
                  <hi>He that is ſlow to wrath, is of great wiſedome, but hee that is of an haſty mind exalteth fooliſhneſse:</hi> ſo that is true like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>He that maiſtereth his affections, is more than he that ſubdueth or conquereth a citie.</hi> And let vs not ſuffer our ſelues to be kept in by full force and ſtrong hand as we ſay, and to forſake and leaue to our enemies, the baſe court, and the whole place it ſelfe. Such cowardiſe we ſhould ſo much the rather auoid, becauſe it draweth after it, fire and fagot, ſacking and pilling, ſlaughter and ſword, euen the very wrath and curſe of God, which followeth him at the heeles, and very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten breaketh out from the Prince vpon the people, and from his cloſet vpon his eſtate. And thus wee ſee how the Prince ſhould hold and reſerue his heart to God, euen againſt his owne eyes, that is to ſay, againſt the corruption, yea againſt the verie Treaſon (as I may
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6835:37"/>tearme it) of his ſences.</p>
               <p>But euen without, there are beſides his owne corruptions, ſundrie other people, that ſlauiſhly offer themſelues vnto him, to feed his fantaſie, and bring him his pleaſures, yea put his delights as it were into his hands. Theſe are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon plague-ſores in Princes pallaces, and very poyſoners indeed of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like fountaines, from whence ſo many millions of people and perſons haue to draw the water that they muſt drinke. But <hi>Dauid</hi> will keepe himſelfe from theſe, there is his care: and admoniſh others to beware of them, and therein he expreſſeth his loue. And this is the cauſe why in the very next words hee ſaith, That <hi>he hateth the workes of them that fall away, that nothing thereof ſhall cleaue vnto him.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>he hateth their workes or deeds,</hi> and yet for all that he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not their perſons, but he hateth their plague and their contagion. Hee hateth not them that were infected with the plague, or were leprous: nay rather hee deſired that they might bee healed,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6835:38"/>brought backe to their former health and ſoundneſſe, and as it were ſet in a good way. In which hee notablie ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his diſcretion, diſcerning betweene good and euill, men and matters, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth his loue, labouring the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the corrupt. A notable example for all men, but ſpecially for Magiſtrates to imitate. Howbeit in as much as vice and ſinne is a contagious poyſon, which maketh men infected therewith, no leſſe dangerous to other men, than to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, he proteſteth that he will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them about him, that hee will lodge them without the hoſt of Gods people, <hi>as plaguie perſons, and as leapers were wont to be,</hi> and that nothing that hath touched them, ſhall come nigh him or his. By all which hee would giue vs to vnderſtand, that ſuch kind of men ſhould be farre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued from the cloſets and chambers of earthly kings and Princes, ſhewing that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo farre doth ſunder them from himſelfe, that neither their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, their portions, nor any thing that hath touched them, ſhall come nigh to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6835:38"/>him. Their ſight and preſence, their breath and ſpeech, yea their very appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell ſhould be ſuſpected, and feared to be contagious and infectiue, and that with a more piercing poyſon, than plague or peſtilence, yea the ſame more preſentlie and dangerouſly aſſaulting and hurting than they, becauſe it paſſeth from the bodie to the heart, from the heart to the ſoule, and as it goeth, increaſeth, and multiplieth his ſtrength, according to the proportion and nature of the place which it ſetteth vpon, or taketh hold of, and by conſequent ſpreadeth it ſelf from a groom of the chamber, as we may ſay, to the king, from the king to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, from this preſent age, to and vpon poſteritie to come. So well skilled and able is humane infirmitie to preuaile againſt our power and force. And ſo mightie is vice, when it is armed with authoritie, or hath a powerfull example to countenance it, and yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it ſelfe both feeble and ill born, as it is ſhamleſſe and cowardlie of it owne nature. And therefore not onely
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6835:39"/>in hope of victorie, but in hatred of euil ſpecially, euery good man, in his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but moſt of all euerie godly prince ſhould ſay, as <hi>Dauid</hi> dooth in another Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 6.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Away from me all ye workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</hi> But here the Courtiers will ſay, we deſcribe a monke rather than a man, and paint out rather a pilgrime than a Prince, and a cloiſter or couent, rather than a court. And they will tell vs, that kings muſt haue their pleaſures, and that it was neuer ſeene otherwiſe as yet. And verily, who or what is hee, that plainely perceiueth not this, that the bitterneſſes which accompanie crownes, had need to be ſugred and made ſweet with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures? And who will denie, but that ſo many greefes, ſorrowes, heartbreakings, and headbreakings, as Princes haue, ſhould be mixed with much ioy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light? Wee allow them to others, and they looke to enioy them: much more fit are they for Princes, and they ſhould haue a greater portion thereof, becauſe they haue more meaſure of feare, care, and other humane paſſions. And this
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6835:39"/>wee ſhould verily bee perſuaded of, that becauſe they are become kings, they ceaſe not therefore to bee men like vnto our ſelues, but rather for that ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo much the more men, by how much they haue more occaſion for mans corruption to worke vpon, than mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner people. Neither is it needfull, that to be kings, they ſhould bee fruſtrate or depriued of honeſt pleaſures, but rather that they ſhould be furniſhed with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly graces, both to make them meet for their callings, and to inſtruct them to vſe theſe pleaſures well. Yea I ſay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that beſides theſe pleaſures which they haue and may vſe as men, I would haue them to haue pleaſures of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt excellencie that may bee: I would haue them to haue pleaſures indeed roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and wel fitting and beſeeming kings, that as their places are greater than others, ſo their pleaſures might farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed others. Yea I would further haue theſe pleaſures to be ſo great and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto them, that for them they ſhould forget their other pleaſures, yea that the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6835:40"/>other in compariſon of them, ſhould become and bee counted diſpleaſures. Thinke but a little of this I beſeech you, what pleaſure <hi>Dauid</hi> receiued, yea what deepe and inward pleaſure he had in his ſoule, when notwithſtanding the ſpight and malice of the Philiſtims, hee <hi>had brought the arke of God into the city of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sa. 6.2. &amp;c</note> A man would haue ſuppoſed, that hee had almoſt forgotten his dignitie, and that hee had loſt his countenance and kingly grace, if he ſhould haue ſeen him daunce, skip, and leape, euen as if it had beene out of himſelfe. And his wife <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal,</hi> a verie patterne of worldlie wits, frumpeth him for it, and ſaith: <hi>O how glorious was the king of Iſrael this day.</hi> But hee telleth her plainely, <hi>That that hee did was before the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Sa. 6.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>who choſe him rather than her father &amp; all his houſe. And if that were to bee vile, hee would bee yet more vile than ſo. Salomon</hi> his ſonne likewiſe, when he ſaw the temple furniſhed, and beheld the ſeruice of God ſetled, and placed therein, for which great fauour alſo, hee did ſo ſolemnly thanke God, as is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6835:40"/>who I ſay is able to conceiue in his heart the great ioy that hee receiued thereby? Or who would ſet in a bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance againſt it thoſe worldly vanities that men commonly call pleaſures? And ſuch were the pleaſures of <hi>Conſtantine, Theodoſius,</hi> and of <hi>Charles</hi> the great. Such were the pleaſures of theſe great kings and Emperours that conquered the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, &amp; were protectors of the church. Yea in our age that great king <hi>Frauncis,</hi> ſo much renoumed in all his pleaſures, as no man more, yet gained little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereby, but the ſpoiling and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of himſelf, his wealth and ſtrength, he as it were rotting in them. And yet euen for that little labor and loue which he gaue vnto vertue, and imploied about learning, hee liueth, and is worthily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred euen to this day, and ſhall liue for many ages hereafter. The leaſt and laſt houre of his life almoſt, being well imploied, was of more worth than all his yeares before, and that was it that got him the name of Great, made his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6835:41"/>verie famous.</p>
               <p>But behold Chriſtendome, ſince that time hitherto, for many years together, toſſed wich differences and diuerſities in religion, ſtates troubled vnder that pretext, and the people beaten downe, yea vtterly ruinated. All ſigh and grone vnder the burthen of their calamine, all breath after and deſire ſome reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſome better eſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if it might bee. Thinke with your ſelues what great loue ſhould that king purchaſe at the hands of his age, and what glorie ſhould he procure in poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to come, what peace and ioy in his owne ſoule, that ſhould build againe the Lords temple, that ſhould reare vp his alters, that ſhould purge his ſeruice fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corruption, and ſhould by theſe good meanes, and ſuch like, compound ſchiſmes, diuiſions, partialities in the church, in the State, and euery where breaking forth? And ſhould take from robbers and Tyrants all the matter and occaſion of their conſpiracies; and of their monopolies, and priuate profites?
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6835:41"/>and ſhould giue a breathing ſpace to ſo many millions of peoples, and to ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n infinite number of perſons, aſſurance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or their goods, freedom to their bodies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt to their ſoules? And ſhould draw or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull from vnder ſo confuſed a Chaos, and heape of all exceſſe and outrage, a good gouernement, a certaine and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led order, and a cheerefull light? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely I perſuade my ſelfe, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple euen of a certaine earneſt deſire, and vnfained good will to ſuch, would kiſſe their apparrell, and reuerence euerie thing that did belong to them, yea they would reioice exceedingly. And good reaſon, becauſe they were reſtored as it were from death to life, and from all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, to all mercie both outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. And I thinke verily, that ſuch a prince with ſo many clappings of hands, and bleſſings, as he ſhould receiue, wold goe out of his bodie, and bee void of his ſences, and become altogether ſpirit, and altogether ſoule, ſo farre off would he bee to thinke vpon, or make account of theſe poor pleaſures that men eſteem
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6835:42"/>to bee ſuch. Theſe are the pleaſures of a king, yea theſe are the pleaſures that I wiſh with al my heart, might be heaped, <hi>with meaſure preſsed downe, and running ouer,</hi> vpon my king: pleaſures pure, and free from all diſpleaſures and greeffe, which to thinke vpon, or remember, is full of honour, of profit, of ioy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the pleaſure and ſweetneſſe alſo, doth not wither or decay; pleaſures, by which hee approcheth to God, and is exalt ed aboue honour it ſelfe: and not thoſe vict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſinful pleaſures, which creep vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, and cauſe a Prince to bee a priuate perſon, and a man a beaſt as it were, as wee ſee particularly in <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnetzar,</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned in <hi>Daniels</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,<note place="margin">Dani. 4.30.</note> and as <hi>Hoſhea</hi> ſheweth it in plaine ſpeeches,<note place="margin">Hoſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.11.</note> ſaying, <hi>Whoredome and Wine, and new wine, take away the hart.</hi> But tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſuch pleſaures, the king I ſpeake of, will ſay as <hi>Dauid</hi> doth, <hi>I will flie from both the perſons that fall away, and the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings away themſelues: nothing that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to them, ſhall approch vnto mee.</hi> But <hi>Dauid</hi> made a vow concerning two
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6835:42"/>points. Firſt, that hee would be vpright in all his judgements. And this reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth other men, with whom hee ſhould haue to deale, and is as I may ſay publike or common. The ſecond, that he would be pure and cleane in his conuerſation. But this concerneth himſelfe, and may bee tearmed priuat. Howbeit good alſo, <hi>whileſt other men ſeeing his holy conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion coupled with feare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>might learne to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God in the day of their viſitation.</hi> And both theſe are according to the double perſon that he ſuſtained; as he was a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat man, holy life for good example was fit: and as hee was a king or Magiſtrat, execution of iuſtice was more than ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie. Otherwiſe, if hee had failed in both, hee had deſtroied both waies, and if hee had failed in the one, and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the other, hee had as faſt pulled downe as ſet vp. And thereſore that he might be the better holpen and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to them both, hee ſaith of the one, That hee will flie both the occaſion and the contagion thereof, and contains his eies, and vtterly abſtaine from the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6835:43"/>wicked. And for the other, the better to preſerue the integrity of his reaſon, and of his iudgement, yea his vprightneſſe, as well towards his neighbours, as to his ſubiects, hee ſayth and promiſeth to practiſe himſelfe that which hee had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, and therefore he addeth:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 4.</hi> A froward heart ſhall depart from mee: I will not know or allow of euill, or of an euill perſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y theſe words, froward heart, <hi>Dauid</hi> meaneth ſuch a one as hateth the vpright way that he propoſed vnto himſelfe, and propounded to others to follow and walke in. And the reaſon thereof is expreſſed in <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> ſaying. <hi>Hee that walketh in vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſsee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>feareth the Lord, but he that goeth by odde courſes in his way, deſpiſeth him.</hi> And why ſhould not wee take it to be ſuch a ſinne indeed, euen contempt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6835:43"/>of God, when diſpightfylly we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the way of good workes, which hee hath prepared for vs to walke in, and will follow by-paths of our own and of other mens deuiſe? But if a man would take it more largely, ſpecially ſince the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our firſt Parents hath entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, wee ſhall ſee, that our vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, yea the vprightneſſe of all and euerie one of vs, is ſo vitiate and corrupted, that none can bee counted better than peruerſe and froward, be he what hee may bee in his owne or other mens iudgement. Howbeit, here he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them peruerſe or froward, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in their frowardnes, yea that pleaſe and flatter themſelues ſo much therein, that in their frowardneſſe and peruerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, they will not ſpare to peruert and corrupt all things, euen the good courſe of honeſt life, and the very lawes which are eſtabliſhed to redreſſe things amiſſe: whereas good people knowing their owne imperfection, ſtoope down to the lawes, and vnder the lawes, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them inforce to reforme, both
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6835:44"/>their heart inwardly, and their life out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, knowing that they haue need of this, and all other good meanes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe and reforme the world of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that is within them. Hee had ſaid before, <hi>I will ſtudie in the right way.</hi> Away then from me muſt all thoſe that peruert their paths, and lead themſelues as hee ſaith in another place, <hi>to crooked waies.</hi> He ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſ. 125.5.</note> 
                  <hi>That he would execute right iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Therefore they muſt depart, that peruert iudgement: concerning whom it is written in the law: <hi>Curſed be hee that maketh a man to goe out of his way:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut 27.18. Deut. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.17.</note> 
                  <hi>curſed be he that peruerteth the right,</hi> yea indeed they are doublie accurſed, becauſe they peruert and corrupt kings and their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and becauſe they make peoples and kings to become accurſed of God. For ſaith he,<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.26.</note> 
                  <hi>With the froward, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf froward:</hi> euen thou O Lord (ſaith hee) whoſe ordinarie way is goodneſſe and mercie, yet ſometimes, and in ſome things, thou art pleaſed to go aſide from that way of thine, to the end thou maieſt exerciſe thy moſt iuſt wrath againſt the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6835:44"/>peruerſe and froward. But concerning the point: this we may certainely hold, that the ſoule euen of the beſt (if there be any one better than another) is of it ſelfe, ſo infirme, and ſo lowable, ſpecially to euill, both in the will, and in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding thereof, that it needeth not either props or obiects, to prouoke the vprightneſſe of it, or to draw it away, for of it ſelfe it can doe nothing, but ſee, delight in, and performe euil. Nay rather it hath need of all ſtops and ſtaies, to hinder it therefrom, and of all good and gracious helpes, to hold and keepe it in well doing. Doe not we ſee, that one ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word corrupted or peruerted, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the law? One masked or diſguiſed circumſtance altereth an action: one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct: ſpeech, or a little Sophiſtrie, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planteph iudgement? And from thence flow thoſe falſe decrees, ordinances; and ſentences, that kings and ſtates many times make and giue out. Such was that of <hi>Achab,</hi> when he accuſed <hi>Elias, to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ſtate.</hi> And ſo likewiſe was that of the Phariſees, when they charged our
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:6835:45"/>and Maginrates, for not preuenting euil in other, as for performing it in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And great reaſon, becauſe they haue infinite more meanes to prouoke to well doing and obedience, than the meaner ſort. And therefore <hi>Dauid,</hi> who knew that God had authoriſed him, and that God was in him, ſpeaketh after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort. Yea (ſaith hee) <hi>I will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge nor aduow them:</hi> that is, as wee would ſay in plaine Engliſh, I will not account them for mine, or any manner of way belonging vnto me. They ſhall not at any hand attend vpon mee, or in any thing ſerue me. Hee ſpake it of ſuch as fell away, and were out of order, and vnruly, of whom alſo hee ſaith, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing belonging vnto them, ſhall ſo much as once touch him. As though hee ſhould ſay: I will haue nothing of theirs: and I will doe it to this end, that they may not corrupt me. He ſpeaketh it as wee haue heard alreadie, of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and froward, of thoſe ſame blacke and wicked ſoules, they ſhall touch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that is mine, they ſhall haue no
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6835:45"/>part or fellowſhip with me. And this wil I doe, to the end they may not abuſe or deceiue me. He meaneth that he would not communicate vnto them, or beſtow vpon them any part of his authoritie, of his dignitie, of his ſtrenght: no that hee would not ſo farre forth as lay in him, beſtow vpon them either offices or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. For this is certaine, hee that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth the peruerſe and froward, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth them in themſelues, as in regard of their own minds, and amongſt others alſo. In themſelues, becauſe that euill in creaſeth them in ſtrength and power. For the more wicked the men are that are aduance, the greater euill doe they commit, becauſe they haue power in their hands. In others, becauſe it ſtirreth vp by the ſame arguments of honour, of preferment and power, a wicked b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and ſtock, that is in men readie to ſprout out, by that bad example, and abu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of that holy authoritie that is beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. Wheras without it, ſuch a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man could be able to doe nothing: hee could hurt none but himſelfe, and it
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6835:46"/>may be that his poiſon (becauſe he could not euaporate and vent it) would ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle himſelfe, and ſtop his breath. But make ſuch a one a Magiſtrate, and wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inſueth? Iuſtice is deſtroied, becauſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is exalted, is vniuſt: religion ſhall be ſuppreſſed, becauſe hee that is irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, or hath no care of true religion, but rather is an enemie to it, is aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And this wee may be ſure of it, ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be ſo much the greater, by how much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he power and proportion whereunto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſhall be lifted vp (be it in Church o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Commonweale, in a Citie, in a country in an eſtate) ſhall be high and great. But ſpecially put the ſword into his hand and then you ſhall ſee nothing but rage inſolencie, extortion, and all manner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> crueltie, as though ſome new <hi>Pharoah</hi> or <hi>Phalaris</hi> were raiſed vp. Or commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto him the keeping of the bag, and then you ſhal ſee nothing but catching and ſnatching, craft and couetouſneſſe yea very trecherie and treaſon, as if the ſpirit of old <hi>Iudas,</hi> were raiſed vp from the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:6835:46"/>
Kings thinke to waſh their hands from this wickednes when they be ſorie or greeued for it. Though that be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, and indeed much more than ſuch mightie men many times practiſe, yet it will not ſerue their turne. <hi>Pilat</hi> by that ceremonie thought to cleare himſelfe of Chriſts innocent and guiltleſſe bloud, but all that notwithſtanding, hee was a murtherer. The thing that deceiueth them is this: They conſider not that they ſhall render an account thereof: neither conſider they, that of all theſe enormious and ſore ſtrokes that fall vpon their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they are the very firſt mouers and authors, and the wel-ſprings fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they flow, becauſe they haue placed ſuch ouer the people, as can doe nothing but oppreſſe. As for the officers themſelues, euen thoſe that make the greateſt adoe in their places, they are nothing els but ſtaues in the hands of the wicked to ſtrike withall. He that giueth authoritie and power to a wicked man, committeth a foule offence. For hee auoweth and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth all the euill that he doth, yea hee
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6835:47"/>aſſiſteth him to doe it, becauſe hee len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him his hand, yea he doth it indeed becauſe his power performeth the ſame. And reaſon will ſhew it vs. In actions that depend vpon vs, and bee in our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer as we ſay, to doe, there is ſmall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt ſuffering them to bee done, and the doing of them, vnleſſe it bee that to ſuffer them, ſeemeth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be the more faultie. This wil be thought a paradoxe in reaſon and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: but weigh this well I beſeech you. Hee that doth it, is moued with proſit, and receiueth ſome aduantage by it: and the more he hath of temptation the leſſe hee hath of ſinne. But hee that ſuffereth it, receiueth domage by it, in his honor, in his ſubiects, in his eſtate. In his honor, becauſe it is impaired by euill: in his ſubiects, becauſe they are oppreſſed and made worſe by bad example: and in his ſtate, becauſe by ſinne he haleth downe vpon it iudgement and confuſion. If he were but an indifferent and meane man, as much inclined to good as to euil, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that hee would not haue the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6835:47"/>euill done, that hee would not ſuffer it, ſpecially ſeeing that there is adioined with it his owne domage and hurt. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it, is now no more paſſion, as wee may ſay, it is action, yea it is worſe than the action, becauſe hee that ſuffereth it, taketh pleaſure therein. And to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in ſinne, is as bad, if not worſe than ſinne: and the rather becauſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in a feeling and fearefull heart ſaith: <hi>If I delight in euill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.18.</note> 
                  <hi>God will not heare my praiers.</hi> And a ſtrange metamorphoſis doth ſinne make, when it doth alter and change the nature of things, turning paſſion into action, as hath been ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This is a very goodleſſon for prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. They will haue the praiſe and the profit of ſuch victories, as wherein their generals and captaines fight and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, and the credite and glory of the conqueſts, in which their lieutenants haue laboured, and taken ſore paine. And yet they will make themſelues and others beleeue, that they are not parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the blame and ſhame of their euill Magiſtrates, and vnmeet Officer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:6835:48"/>when they commit iniuſtice, and of the ſinne of their courtiers, when they doe violence, and of their treaſurers and exchequer men, when they doe extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But the law ſaith: <hi>Hee that hath the profit, he muſt alſo indure the paine and the domage.</hi> And if mans law in die light of nature could ſay ſo, no doubt but Gods law in the preciſe equitie thereof will much more affirme it. And ſith the labour likewiſe of the ſeruant belongeth to his Maiſter, whether hee doe well or ill: no doubt but hee that will tyth the paines, the labour, and the valour of all men, and bring it to his owne pleaſure, to his owne profit, to his owne praiſe, muſt thinke alſo to haue the ſelfeſame, portion, in the diſgrace, in the euill ſpeech, and in the paine that falleth out at other times. My meaning is this, that ſith from the loſſe of ſundry mens liues, the kings of the earth draw glorious victories, and from diuerſe mens purſes, great and infinite treaſures, neither of which they haue made, or can make, that therefore certainely and indeed by verie
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6835:48"/>good reaſon it muſt needs inſue, that ſeeing it is either through the Princes default, or through his deed, that manie iniuries and iniuſtices are committed by them whom he hath negligently and careleſly eſtabliſhed in the gouernment, he muſt needs vndergoe a iuſt condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation therefore.</p>
               <p>Now from actions and deeds, <hi>Dauid</hi> commeth conſequently to deale with words: and from the heart (the very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer or mouing of actions) he paſſeth to the tongue, the very inſtrument and meane of ſpeech: the tongue I ſay,<note place="margin">I am. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>which</hi> (as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith) <hi>defileth the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and ſetteth all the world on fire, but in the end</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is ſet on fire by hell it ſelfe.</hi> Wheretore wee haue need of great aid to reſtraine and repreſſe this fire, which wil caſt vs, if we auoid it not, into a moſt fearefull fire, of endleſſe death and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. And therefore the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> preſently addeth, ſaying:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:6835:49"/>
               <head>Verſe 5. <hi>He that priuily woundeth his neighbor with his tongue, I will cut him off</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the ſame verſe, paſſing from words to thoughts and geſtures of loftineſſe, hee ſaith: <hi>He that hath his eyes lifted vp, and a groſse or high heart, I can at no hand ſuſſer or indare him.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold mercies that <hi>Iob</hi> in Gods name promiſeth to them that feare the Lord, this is one:<note place="margin">Iob. 5.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord ſhall deliuer thee from the force and power of the ſword: hee ſhall hide thee from the ſcourge of the tongue.</hi> If we marke theſe words well, we ſhall ſee, that there is as wee ſay, a grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them. For his ſpeech aſcendeth, and his meaning is, That the tongue is no leſſe dangerous and hurtfull than the ſword. Nay rather it ſeemeth to bee
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6835:49"/>more dangerous indeed, and that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpects, as firſt it pierceth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth further than the ſword can: then the ſtripes &amp; blows of it are more ſecret and cloſe. Laſtly, they hurt not the bodie onely, but the good name: in all which, reſpects alſo, they are ſurely more hard to be healed and holpen: which though it bee true, as in reſpect of all men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, yet the neerer they are to Princes, that vſe to ſtrike with that weapon, the more greeuous and great are thoſe wounds and blowes. Great I ſay, becauſe the tongue there, prouoketh, yea infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a very great and mightie power, yea ſuch apower, <hi>as hath</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>in the outward part of his lips, death or life.</hi> Great againe I ſay, becauſe it is skilfull to poſſeſſe beforehand, and to peruert an eare, that is verie much buſied: and by conſequent more meet to beleeue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric matter, than to direct or order all, or any thing. <hi>Diocleſian</hi> the Emperour was a verie wiſe Prince, and in his wiſe dome he could truly ſay, <hi>That two or three cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers could quickly ſeize or take hold of a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6835:50"/>Princes care.</hi> What meant hee thereby? Surely this: that by ſuch mens means he did vnderſtand euery thing: they cauſed him ſometimes to looke this way, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that way, and to carrie ſuch coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances to or againſt others, as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelues, wherein many times their ſinne by abuſe of the tongue was the greater, by how much they did not onely ſpeake beſides or againſt truth, but deliuered deceit and falſehood. By which we may ſee, how much it impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all ſorts and ſtates of people, but ſpecially princes and great perſonages, that the tongues which are about them, ſhould be pure and cleane, and exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and freed to the vttermoſt, from the poyſon of lying, flatterie, detraction, and other ſuch groſſe corruptions: which, (if the paſſage thereof bee not ftopped) will ſlide from the care to the heart, from the heart to the head, and from the head to the hands of a Prince, and ſo ſhall iniquitie be perfected.</p>
               <p>Princes hands wee ſay, whether it bee for euill, or for good, are of verie
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:6835:50"/>large reach, euen vnto the skirts &amp; bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of a very great Empire and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yea many times vnto other mens territories and gouernments. The blows and ſtrokes which they giue, are verie fore and heauie, euen according to the proportion of the Prince himſelfe: and yet they are but ſet on worke, or thruſt forward by a very light &amp; ſleight toung, which afterwards can neither call theſe blowes backe againe, nor repaire the breaches that they haue made. But if wicked tongues bee domageable and hurtfull to Princes ſeruants, as they are, becauſe they make them to become flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, falſe witneſſe bearers, &amp;c. they muſt needs bee much more hurtfull to Kings and Princes themſelues, if they once draw nigh to their perſons and preſence, becauſe through ſlaunder, and lying, and ill ſpeech, they trouble their eſtates, and by flatterie, they blind the Princes owne eies. And therefore in this reſpect, good men haue good cauſe to ſay as the Prophet doth:<note place="margin">Pſa. 52.1.2 3. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Why boaſlteſt thou thy ſelfe in thy wickedneſſe, O man of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6835:51"/>power? The louing kindneſſe of God indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth daily. Thy tongue imagineth miſcheefe, and it like a ſharpe raſor that cutteth deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. Thou doeſt loue euill more than gord, and lies more than to ſpeake the truth: thou loueſt all words that may deſtroy, O deceitfull tongue. So ſhall God deſtroy thee for euer. Hee ſhall take thee and plucke thee out of thy tabernacle, and root thee out of the land of the liuing.</hi> Wherein it ſhall not bee amiſſe to marke how and after what ſort the tongue proceedeth, &amp; effecteth theſe euill things. By ill ſpeech they diſguiſe good mens actions and deeds, and ſet another manner of hue and ſhape vpon them, than indeed they beare. And the better men are, the worſe are they ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. The reaſon, becauſe that their proceeding being leſſe cloſe &amp; colored, their goodnes and wel doing is ſo much the more laid open to calumnie and ſlaunder: that we may ſay nothing of the hatefull hart that the wicked carrie againſt them. And this is certaine, that where ſlaunder ſeeth the fleſh naked, or a man laid open, it will not with <hi>Shem</hi> and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6835:51"/>
                  <hi>Iapheth</hi> couer it, but rather with <hi>Ham</hi> reioice at it, yea there it taketh occaſion with the wicked of the world to inſult and triumph, there it nippeth, and there it biteth, becauſe elſewhere to aſſay it, it were but loſt labour, and the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of their owne teeth. And what are the effects that flow from this euill? The better the men are, the more ſenſible and feeling are they, the ſooner offended and greeued, and by meanes thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin liuely to be touched, yea being tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched indeed, either they become male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content as we ſay, or at the leaſt thrown downe into deſpaire of their ſtate, and paſt hope of recouerie, they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnfit, either for publike or priuat, and vnprofitable almoſt for any implo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And from hence come ſo many diſgraces offered them from abroad, ſo many iuſt forrows and ſighings in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felues, by means wherof the country and Commonwealth, haue oftentimes been ſpoiled of worthie perſons, and beſides theſe noble and worthie ſpirits, caſt downe in themſelues, and diſgraced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6835:52"/>the world. And theſe and fundrie ſuch like are the fruits of ſlaunder or ill ſpeech. But flatterie is much worſe, and more dangerous by much, for by it the Prince is diſguiſed to himſelfe, yea he is ſo ſubtellie deceiued, that hee doth not any longer know himſelfe, or his owne eſtate, turning his vice into vertue, his crueltie into iuſtice, his cowardiſe and faint-heartedneſſe into clemencie and mercie, telling him that his words are Oracles, that his lawes are aboue all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and nature whatſoeuer, that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is not Gods officer, but his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, with a thouſand other ſuch Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renian ſongs: ſo much the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, yea deadly, by how much the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is great that is corrupted therby, and the effects flowing therefrom, deſperate, and paſt recouerie. Surely, ſurely, theſe are not onely cloſe and ſecret, but dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and deadly wounds For it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the ſtories of all ages and times, that theſe adulations and flatteries, theſe adorations and worſhippings haue very quietly, and almoſt without anie ſence or
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6835:52"/>feeling, brought the moſt mighty Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the world to their end, as if it were oxen that did weare the garland againſt the day of their ſlaughter. Nature tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the quite and clean contrary. And wee ſee by experience that Chirurgians heale, when they hurt and put to paine. Wheras flatterers tonugs kil men, when they would ſeem to tickle and pleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The feeling knowledge of this point, made <hi>Dauid</hi> elfewhere both to pray and ſay: <hi>Let me not eat the delicats of the wicked.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 141.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Let the righteous rather ſmite me, for that is a benefit, and let him reproue me, and it ſhall be a precious oyle that ſhall not breaks my head.</hi> meaning, that the reprooſes of the righteous, yea his very wounds &amp; ſtripes are as a precious baulme or oyle, to help and heale. And <hi>Salomon</hi> after him: <hi>The chiding or rebuke of the wiſe, is much better than the ſong of the ſoole.</hi> And therefore much better indeed is the free ſpeech of a good and faithfull ſeruant, than the inchanting words of flatterers. Wiſe Princes in the world, haue alwaies taken great heed to keepe themſelues ſafe and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6835:53"/>ſure from ſuch people. Hence is it, that euen the Heathen could ſay, <hi>It is better to fall into the hands of crowes &amp; cormorants, than to come amongſt flatterers.</hi> And they haue rendred this reaſon of it: <hi>For thoſe doe but prey vpon dead carkaſſes, and thoſe eat vpliuing men.</hi> And we read of ſundry great kings, who fearing that their fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, courtiers, and attendants, did ſet a better colour vpon cauſes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were worthie of, or had indeed, would now and then diſſemble their ſtates and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that ſo from the common ſort they might the better vnderſtand that which they could not by their friends and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourites. This was a good intent and purpoſe I confeſſe, but not well guided or ordered. For what could they learne thereby but the common voice of the people (as wee ſay) which is as readie to blame the good, as to accuſe the euill, yea many times more ready to that than to this, becauſe as the wife man ſayth, <hi>The iuſt is an abhomination to the wicked:</hi> and our Sauiour telleth vs, <hi>that the world will loue his owne.</hi> But the truth is, kings
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:6835:53"/>that are wiſe indeed, will practiſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of matter, and keepe a farre other courſe. They will chuſe vertuous people, and place them about them, and they will giue all manner of libertie to thoſe that are not paſſionate, to ſpeake vnto them: yea they will open their mouths that are fit to ſpeak, and will take in good part their good aduertiſements and councels, yea they wil profit by their accuſations, whether they bee bent againſt their actions, or againſt their perſons and liues. And good reaſon it ſhould bee ſo: For they ſpeake from a ſound heart, and direct their words to religious and right ends. And beſides the wiſe man telleth vs: <hi>A faithfulfriend is the medicine of life: it purgeth the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and correcteth the actions.</hi> And the ſame wiſe man addeth, ſaying: <hi>Hee that ſeareth the Lord, ſhall find ſuch a one.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f we ſhould profit by that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vntruly, and with an vnſound and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atefull heart, that ſo we may bring out of mens darkeneſſe the ſound light of faithful obedience, <hi>as wee ſee Dauid did
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6835:54"/>at the railing of Shimei:</hi> Should we not much more make vſe of that which is deliuered truly, as in regard of matter, dutifully, as in reſpect of manner, and ſoundry as in regard of affection?</p>
               <p>This is a doctrine and leſſon moſt neceſſarie for Princes to learne, who in ſteed of opening ſuch mens mouths, muſt ſtop and ſhut their owne eares againſt them: and in ſteed of laying open their hearts vnto them, muſt pull out their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies and their tongues, &amp; hold this for a certaine and ſure ſaying that they haue receiued a great mercie from God and man, when they haue eſcaped, or are deliuered from ſuch. Wee haue ſeene and heard of ſome Princes, that hauing been hurt and wounded, haue deſired the Chirurgians to thinke them, and to take them for priuate ſouldiours, and neuer to cocker them, or to reſpect them. Why did they ſo? They knew full well, that to heale them, and to flatter them, were things that could not well ſtand together. And this they could doe for bodily health and ſtrength. How
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:6835:54"/>much more ſhould they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as if it were priuate perſons, to good and vertuous people, that ſo they might helpe and heale the maladies of their mind, or their vices. Wee will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly reach out, and ſuffer the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to feele our pulſes: and wee will lay open or diſcouer our plague ſore to the Barber or Chirurgian. And why do we not the like for our ſpirituall ſickneſſes? Nay rather wee are ſicke of a contrarie humour, for wee will not diſcouer our vices, or our imperfections to any but ſuch as ſhall foſter and cheriſh them in vs. If any man ſpeake plaine, wee are of <hi>Achabs</hi> mind:<note place="margin">1. Kin. 22.8.</note> 
                  <hi>there is one man Michaiah the ſonne of Imlah, but I hate him, for hee doth not prophecie good vnto me, but euill.</hi> Wee cannot indure, that one ſhould ſo much as touch them, vnleſſe it be to tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle them, and as it were with a certaine pleaſant delight in them, to lull vs aſleep therein. And yet for all this I am not of thoſe mens minds that would haue great perſons, at all times, without any diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or difference, to be reproued. Some
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:6835:55"/>thinke the hatred of euill in others, and the dutie that is laid vpon them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh or reproue, doth make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as in regard of the manner. But they are fouly deceiued, for euery good thing muſt be done well, and wee are tied, not onely to matter, but to maner of doing, yea to ſuch a forme as God hath ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto vs in his word. Princes perſons are great I confeſſe, and their places high, I acknowledge that alſo, but they doe not either priuiledge the Princes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from inſtruction, admonition, or rebuke: or intitle priuate and particular perſons to doe it, when, where, and as they will. <hi>Nathan</hi> Gods owne Prophet proceedeth not therein after ſuch a ſort. He made his entrance into the king, by windings about and fetches,<note place="margin">c. Samu. 21.12. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>euen by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables and darke ſpeeches</hi> at the firſt: then he defended ſoftely and gently to charge him with the ſin, &amp; at the laſt to threaten him for his tranſgreſſion. I will ſay no more but this, vſe what reuerence you will, or what art you can, only let them thinke you ſee their finnes, and doe you
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:6835:55"/>your beſt endeauour to cauſe them to feele ſorrow for it (<hi>yea a godlie ſorrow which cauſeth repentance vnto ſaluation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>neuer to he repented of</hi>) and to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the danger of it, that ſo you may preuent the accidents and the occaſions of a canker. So <hi>Nathan</hi> ceaſed not to purge <hi>Dauid</hi> from his ſinne: he ſquiſed and cruſhed out the matter and filth of it, he preſſed vpon him confeſſion of it, contrition for it, and ſound conuerſion vnto God, and all bathed in the bitter teares of a faithfull ſoule. And what doth this great king for that? Doth hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him ſilence? No, for that had ben impious. Doth he forbid him comming into his preſence? No neither, for that had been inhumane, as in regard of the Prophet, and hurtfull to <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe. Or doth hee diſgrace him in the ſight of his ſubiects, nobilitie, or ſuch like? No ſuch matter, for that had been the deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Gods owne ordinance. What then? He imbraceth him as his faithfull friend, and loueth him ſo much the more heartilie, for that he had delt ſo plainely
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:6835:56"/>and ſoundly with him, in a cauſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his ſoule. And good reaſon, <hi>for open rebuke is better than ſecret loue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 27.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; the words of a louer are faithfully, and the kiſses of an enemie are pleaſant.</hi> Beſides, he was a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie inſtrument to beget him againe to God, and to bring him againe into the Lords fauour, from which <hi>he was ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by meanes of his ſinnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 59.2.</note> and therefore in theſe reſpects alſo to bee beloued. But what would a flatterer haue done here? He would haue left him in his ſinne, and haue let him alone <hi>defiled in his own blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech.16.6.</note> polluted with his ordure, beaten downe with the curſe of God againſt him, and humbled with the hatred of his ſubiects, and all for his ſinnes ſake, and the iuſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of his tranſgreſſion. But what man of pitie in himſelf, of pietie to God, or of charitie towards men, could leaue a man in ſuch a miſerable taking? And yet wee ſee flatterers doe it daily. They wound men cloſely, and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both the perſons, and the dignities of kings, whileſt they make them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that they alter and change the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:6835:56"/>of their vices.<note place="margin">Luke 10.37.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt in the goſpell commendeth the Samaritan for kindneſſe ſhewed to the wounded man:</hi> and vpon it inferreth this doctrine, <hi>that wee muſt goe, and doe likewiſe.</hi> But ſurely hee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne theſe, not onelie for want of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the good they ought to haue done, bur for doing the euill they ſhould not haue done.</p>
               <p>And princes are not in danger this way alone, by flattery I meane: but euen by ſilence alſo. For it may, yea it dooth many times ſo fall out, that euen kings fauorits and familiers, doe no leſſe hurt or euill by holding their peace, than the other do by ſpeaking. Silence is another abuſe of the tongue, becauſe God and nature hath made this proper and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar vnto it, to ſpeake good things, and in due time. But herein is our corruption manifeſted, and Sathans malice alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, that when wee may not ſpeake the euill thinges we ſhould not, wee will not ſpeake the good things we ought. A Sentinell or watchman that is ſilent or holdeth his peace, doth no leſſe betray a
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:6835:57"/>town or citie, than a ſpie or a traitor that ſpeaketh. And that alſo is the reaſon why the law ſayth: <hi>that he is as culpable before the prince that ſpeaketh not of the euill hee knoweth or heareth, as he that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the euill himſelfe.</hi> Thou feareſt belike to offend the eare. And yet thou feareſt not to offend or hurt the ſoule. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the greateſt, if both were offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? Or which ſhouldeſt thou in holy wiſdome, and good nature moſt reſpect? reaſon without religion, I thinke will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily teach thee. And then no ſmall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion ſurely doeſt thou commit, that in laying thy hand vpon thy mouth, blotteſt out religion and reaſon, with the light therof in thy ſelfe, &amp; neglecteſt a more than neceſſarie dutie to Prince, people, kingdome, and all. Know this of a ſuretie, that ſo oft as thou concealeſt any thing, and canſt conueniently or poſſibly reueale it, thou woundeſt the kingly Maieſtie, and his eſtate alſo. If an ambuſh were laid againſt his perſon or power, thou wouldeſt carefully tell him thereof, yea thou wouldeſt, though
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:6835:57"/>it were rudely and roughly, pull him from any place where hee might be too much ſeene, and ſo by conſequent in danger: and thou wouldeſt hale him, ſo thou mighteſt ſaue him, thou didddſt not care whither. This is well done, but it reacheth onely to his bodie. And what? Wilt thou feare to ſet before him, and to free him if thou canſt, from a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible headlong downefall of his ſoule? No, no, here thou muſt tell him: Gods eie ſeeth thee in theſe diſorders of thine, God will raine downe vpon thee for thy ſinnes, the fire and the flambe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignations, thunders and the lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of his diſpleaſure, euen all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of miſeries and curſes whatſoeuer; he is in his furie readie to fall vpon thee and thy people, yea preſt to poure out ſuch puniſhments, as thou canſt neither take away or remoue, and from which no cloke or colour, no caſtle or defence ſhall be able to ſhelter and defend thee. If thou deale not thus ſoundly with thy king, as in regard of his ſoule, what art thou? Humane lawes ſay, that if thou
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:6835:58"/>neglect it, as in reſpect of his body, thou art a Traitor. Gods law that layeth this dutie vpon thee, will much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee for this crime, and that not onely againſt the Prince, but againſt the Lord himſelfe. And theſe iudgements of God, &amp; wrath of his, are ſuch points indeed, as would bee well and ſeriouſly thought of, and the rather, becauſe hee holdeth the principalities and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the world in his owne hand, and ſetteth vp in them for as long time, as ſeemeth good to his owne wiſdome, ſuch as he ſeeth to bee profitable and fit therefore. And yet on the other ſide, for the iniquities, for the diſſolutions, and for the outrages that men doe commit therein, <hi>tranſlateth them from me people to another nation,</hi> and from a ſtocke, to another familie and kindred. And indeed he that in this behalfe, vſeth not libertie and freedome, doth ſecretly and priuily wound: which yet is the more foule in him, becauſe hee doth it hot ſo much with this reſpect, not to offend or hurt his Maiſter, as for his owne ſake, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:6835:58"/>a regard to his owne particular profit, that ſo hee may not offer iniurie to his fauour and his fortune, as men vſe prophanely to ſay, yea ſo much the more miſcheefe doth hee, becauſe hee would ſeeme to be, and bee taken to bee a right honeſt man, who if he were that, that he would ſeeme to bee, could not bee ſilent againſt that which is euill, nor but ſpeak for that which is good. And this euill is not as in regard of himſelfe onely, for then it were the leſſe to be regarded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it were priuate and particular: but as in reſpect of his Prince &amp; Soueraign, who being a publike perſon, and hauing this euill commitred againſt him, hath with him the publike ſtate endamaged. Who alſo, becauſe ſuch a one holdeth his peace, as he taketh to bee a right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt or holie man, doth ſo much the more flatter himſelfe in his ſinne, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, that becauſe hee that is ſo good, ſpeaketh nothing of it or againſt it, that therefore it is no great or weightie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that that which ſuch good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples eies can indure to ſee, is nothing at
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:6835:59"/>all ſo dangerous, as men would make them beleeue it to be. In the mean while the ſuburbes as I may ſay, yea the whole citie is let on fire, Gods wrath waxeth hote, and breaketh forth againſt mens ſinnes, and all by reaſon of the want of an inciſion, as the Chirurgians vſe to ſay, I meane a free, a liuely, and a pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſpeech. Yea behold further miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheefes and inconueniences that follow vpon this curſed ſilence, as for example, reuolting of the people, diſpoſſeſſing of kings, throwing downe of crownes and ſcepters, and the vtter ruine and ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of States. Where are then theſe good counſellours, that will ſay, that if men would haue beleeued them, all ſhould haue beene much better than it is? Neither had things come to ſuch greeuous diſorder and confuſion? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they haue ben for feare of others, for fauour towards themſelues, for igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the cauſes, and other worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects as mute as fiſhes. But ſurely ſay what they will or can, they themſelues, and the poore Princes that they haue
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:6835:59"/>deceiued, are worthie as in this behalfe, and in theſe ſtormes and tempeſts, to meet that ruinated king, of whome <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> ſpeaketh, flying from the force of his enemies, and auoiding what hee could the murmurings of his ſubiects, to whom if one of thoſe ſilent, yea dum courtiers or counſellours ſhould ſay, I foreſaw all this euill; the Prince might iuſtly call him traitour, and ſtab him to, and tell him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If thou diddeſt foreſee this, it had ben thy dutie then to haue told it me, and not to haue waited a time, to haue ſpoken to me of it out of time, and when it is paſt remedie: for what good getteſt thou by that? Thou doeſt but bewray faintheartedneſſe in thy ſelfe, a fault no way fitting a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fellor of eſtate; little or no loue towards me, whom thou ſhouldeſt haue accounted more deere and precious than thine owne life, and that not only for thine owne priuat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, but the common good of the whole kingdome; and leaſt care towards thy Country or Commonweale, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy common parent, and giuing
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:6835:60"/>thee all good things, thou ſhouldeſt haue againe at the leaſt requited with premonition of euil. But what ſhall ſay? Certainely I know not one (and I would wiſh that it might bee obſerued euery where) that is not culpable of this crime. And I beſeech God of his infinit good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercie, to pardon all of vs, and euerie one of vs. Thoſe that offend by ſpeaking too much to the pleaſure and delight of Princes, doe it doubtleſſe for ſome particular and priuate good to themſelues, which they looke to receiue thereby, and many times obtaine it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. On the other ſide, thoſe that through ſilence diſſemble the euil which they foreſee, ſinne certainely much more greeuouſly, and that not onely as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the ſoure fruits before reherſed, but alſo becauſe they doe themſelues no good, yea they greeuouſly hurt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and others alſo: themſelues, whileſt through ſilence, and winking at tranſgreſſion, <hi>they become partakers of other mens ſinnes:</hi> and others, whileſt they doe not by premonition prouoke
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:6835:60"/>preuention and turning away of euill. By ſpeech ſome at the leaſt reape ſome good, though happily it be but outward, and rather ſeeming ſo to bee, than ſuch indeed. But thoſe that are ſilent, haue nothing, nor do nothing but that which is euill, yea euill indeed. Wherefore <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> vpon very good reaſon ſayth both of the one and the other, <hi>I will cut them off.</hi> And great cauſe ſurely, for they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable people, and not onely ſo, but hurtfull alſo, euen to theirkings, and to their country, and to their owne ſelues? Plants they are that haue no fruit, nor any good thing elſe in them but a ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and yet that ſhaddow to is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and if it bee not deadly, it is well. And therefore they worthy, as vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table wood or trees, <hi>to bee bewen downe, and to be caſt into the fire, yea into that fire which ſhall neuer be put out.</hi> But as wee haue ſaid alreadie, he commeth euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the thoughts: <hi>the lifted vp eyes,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the heart that is puffed vp, I will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer or indure them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To trie out this point, wee need not
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:6835:61"/>goe ſeeke for rules, either of Phiſiogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, for they are for the moſt part falſe or of Anatomie, for they are not alwaies ſure. And indeed, to ſpeake properly, the firſt of theſe, are at the moſt but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecturall, and therefore will not ſteed vs here. And the ſecond is to as ſmall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as poſſiblie may bee in this behalfe. What ſhall we ſay then? Diſcerned they muſt be, that is true. And we can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee better inſtructed than from the things themſelues, ſpecially if God giue vs grace to fetch light from thence. The eyes doubtleſſe bee as it were the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the ſoule. In our eyes, or tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row them, the ſoule it ſelfe looketh: for that is true in reaſon and religion, that we are wont to ſay, the foule feeth by the eye, yea by it many times, it diſcouereth it ſelfe, or cauſeth it ſelfe to bee ſeene; as in regard of the affections thereof. Now haughtie or lifted vp eies, are ſuch eyes as goe beyond their bounds and limits, eyes of preſumption and of pride: eyes lifted vp indeed, I confeſſe that, but not vnto God (for then they would humble
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:6835:61"/>themſelues before ſo high and heauenly a Maieſtie, as good cauſe they haue, and as the poore Publican did, <hi>who durſt not lift vp ſo much as bis eies to heauen</hi>) but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifted vp in themſelues.<note place="margin">Luke 18.13.</note> Such eyes (to be ſhort) that ſee nothing, but they thinke it all belongeth to them, and make an account of it, as too baſe for them, yea as if it were their verie vnderling. And ſuch eies as theſe are, doe alwaies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe, yea argue, a heart of the like condition and nature. Such a heart as cannot or will not containe it ſelfe within his owne boſome or breaſt, ſuch a will as will haue no law, nor meaſure, nor bounds ſet it, which hath al the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereof anſwereable, or proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable thereto, that is to ſay, vnruly, highly conceited, and violent. So wee haue in a few words the deſcription of prowd perſons, as the Scripture calleth them; and againſt which it crieth our ſo lowd, and ſo continually. People they are that God cannot abide: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaid in the Word, <hi>The Lord bringeth the prowd downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their thrones:</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:6835:62"/>and in diuerſe places,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord reſiſteth the prowd.</hi> Yee hee pulleth vp the very roots of prowd peoples and nation, and in their roomes planteth, and that with great honour, the lowly and meeke. And againe, people they are that men cannot brooke or beare: and good reaſon, for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they bee inſupportable to God, to men much more. Whereupon alſo it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſaid, <hi>That a prowd perſon is hatefull to all men:</hi> to the good, becauſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, as other ſinnes, ſo that iniquitie and to the wicked, becauſe they are gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that any is preferred with them, or before them. Yea indeed they are purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as if it were with publike execution. And leaſt of all are they to be born with by kings, or to be ſuffered nigh vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea leſſe there than in any other place whatſoeuer. For beſides that kings are great perſons, and therefore ſhould bee good, yea the beſt of men, as they be the higheſt amongſt them, and ſhould haue none approch vnto them but ſuch as are good indeed, proud perſons about them will doe nothing but leaue in them a ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:6835:62"/>ſpirit touching their preſent great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or a feare of that which is to come, and ſo both thoſe humours fill them full of all vnquietneſſe, and make them vnfit for publike rule. And if Princes be once hurt by theſe, or ſuch like, the damage reſteth not within themſelues, but flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, yea ouerfloweth to all mens hearts. Who for the maintenance of their pride euery way, muſt be pinched in their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, burthened in their bodies, and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in their ſoules. And therefore that wiſe king <hi>Salomon</hi> telleth vs, <hi>that the Lord abhorreth ſeuen things,</hi> and the firſt of them which hee nameth,<note place="margin">Pro. 6.17.</note> are <hi>theſe ſame high lookes, or theſe haughtie and lifted vp eies.</hi> Such fellowes, when they are nigh vnto or about Princes, they make them beleeue, that there is neither law nor king aboue them, and that all that liketh them, is lawfull for them to doe, yea that whatſoeuer they can performe by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, is right and iuſt. Theſe are they that cauſe Princes and themſelues alſo when they are once aloft, to abuſe their greatneſſe, euen according to their own
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:6835:63"/>paſſions and affections. And becauſe they imagine themſelues (though fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vntruly) to bee pettie gods about the Princes whome they gouerne, they cauſe themſelues and their Princes alſo to deſpiſe that great and eternall God which hath ſet them on their ſeats, and as much as in them lieth, exempt them from ſubiection to his Maieſty, and from his homage &amp; ſeruice. Neither are they dangerous to Princes onely, as before hath ben ſhewed, but euen to people al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. For they are like thoſe counſellours that ſaid to <hi>Rehoboam:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Kin. 12.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy father did beat them with rods: thou that haſt more ſtrong reines and loines than he, make them blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die euen with ſcourges and ſcorpions,</hi> yea they are inſtruments of all manner of Tyrannie againſt the people, and by conſequent alſo, meanes of the peoples reuolting from their Princes: all which is euident in <hi>Rehoboams</hi> furie, ten tribes at one time falling away from <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtocke to <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> and neuer afterwards (for ought we can read) adioined ther to ſince: wherein wee are yet to marke fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:6835:63"/>that the more mightie the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs and kings are, about which ſuch prowd perſons are placed, the more pernicions and hurtful are they, by how much they haue a greater power to work vpon, where if once they preuaile, then commeth in iniquitie, not as ſome little flood or riuer, but as the maine ſea, and carrieth all downe before it. And this is it as I think, that is written, where it is ſaid, That for this monſtrous pride <hi>God vngirdeth kings loines, and taketh away from them the girdle of their reines, and depriueth, yea ſpoileth them of their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie, becauſe they haue not done their homage, and their ſeruice vnto him.</hi> Yea and theſe are they alſo, which moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie caſt away their Countries and States, &amp; ouerthrow hoſts and armies, who counſell and perſuade Princes to vniuſt warres, and ſuch as are founded and grounded onely vpon ambition and outward appearance, and when they come to manage them, performe them more vniuſtly. Wherevpon that falleth out which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth: <hi>Humility goeth
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:6835:64"/>before glorie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 11.2.</note> 
                  <hi>but pride no ſooner approcheth, but by and by appeareth ignominy &amp; ſhame.</hi> God verily would not ſuffer prowd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſerue him in heauen, this being moſt likely, the ſin of thoſe <hi>Angels that continued not in their firſt eſtate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iud. verſ. 6.</note> as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of our parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Heuah.</hi> Much leſſe ſhould kings let them raign vnder them in earth. <hi>The beginning of this pride</hi> (as the wiſe man ſheweth vs) <hi>was mans apoſtaſie, reuolting, and ſalling from the Lord</hi> that had made him. And the very end of the pride of Princes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants is this, that after for a while they haue gouerned vnder them, they would at the laſt raigne ouer them, and in their place, or at the leaſtwiſe with them. Much like vnto our Popiſh meritmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who hauing a little while ſerued God, as they ſuppoſe in their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceits, count God to bee ſo tied vnto them, that whether he will, yea or no, they will haue the crowne of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life ſet vpon their heads. And we ſee but too many of ſuch bad diſpoſition both waies. And yet this is ſo much the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:6835:64"/>worſe, becauſe when they are once vp and aloft, they forget al proportion, and all meaſure. The higheſt ſtep of their ſeruice, is the firſt ſtep of their ruling, and to their riſing and getting vp vpon their throne. Whatſoeuer they ſee, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beneath them, or on the one ſide or other of them, is nothing worth. Their eye, their heart, and all is caried to that which is aboue them, and they can neuer be contented in their ſpirits, till they haue attained the ſame, if it may be. Wherefore <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the king wee treat of, will not ſuffer them to violate their greatneſſe, or to offer violence to their people. They are of a farre better mind, than to lay to pledge or to pawne to them, either their authoritie, or their power, much leſſe their affections, or their fauours, or their ſecrets. There is no reaſon, that the vaſſale or ſubiect ſhould receiue and entertaine ſuch as the king or Lord hath baniſhed. If they doe, it will bee found fellonie by law. Such people as God abhorreth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth out of his houſe, earthly kings
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:6835:65"/>(who are vaſſals of that ſoueraigne Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite of his) may not call them backe, nor keepe them cloſe, or cheriſh them about them, neither can the Princes themſelues rightly or by law, open the gate vnto them, and cauſe them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the pallace or any publike place. If they doe ſo, it ſhall bee a ſore offence againſt his Maieſtie, yea treaſon euen of it ſelfe, and therfore they muſt look to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Theſe haughtie hearts, theſe light lips and tongues, theſe violent hands, ſhould not come into the courts of ſuch kings, as either are bleſſed, or would be bleſſed from God. And yet wee ſee, that the world honoureth not but ſuch. He that cannot boaſt and brag by big looks and ſwelling words, is counted but a beaſt. Hee that cannot tell a ſmooth and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant tale, is eſteemed to bee but a paltrie companion. He that cannot ſcratch and catch by booke or by crooke, is a foole, and hath no care for himſelfe and his. If Princes may not haue ſuch, alas, who ſhall they then haue? Not theſe ſurely: for it were better none, than thoſe that
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:6835:65"/>will pill prey for themſelues, and ſpoile and hurt others, euen the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweale. But I will tell you who they ſhould haue, euen ſuch ſurely as God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth leaue to approch moſt nigh vnto himſelfe, and ſuch as hee reckoneth and receiueth for his owne. And ſuch verily and none other ſhould come into their cloſets, or enter into their chamber, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage their matters, execute their offices, and doe whatſoeuer they themſelues are not able by themſelues to doe. And is there not great reaſon for it Shal hee be meet to come into Gods preſence, and ſhall hee haue no place or imployment amongſt the gods of the earth? Or ſhall he not be fit for the Lord of heauen, but baniſhed his bleſſed ſight; and ſhall hee be faithfull &amp; faſt to earthly lords? There is not, as I take it, ſuch cotrariety betwixt God and his owne ordinance, neither ought there to be ſuch great oddes and iarre betwixt the Lord in heauen; and his lieutenants vpon earth. Nay rather ſeeing all that theſe inferiours haue, is from the higheſt, it behoueth them in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:6835:66"/>all things, and therefore in this alſo to reſemble him, that ſo all things retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to him from whom they came, <hi>hee may be all in all.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.28 Pſa. 15.3.4.</note> And this is that the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſayth, <hi>They that walke vprightly, they that hurt not with their tongue, they that haue righteous lips, in whoſe eies the wicked are deſpiſed:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 16.13.</note> but on the other ſide, <hi>hee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth them that feare the Lord,</hi> in what condition or ſtate ſoeuer they bee. And let not Princes for all this, thinke that they ſhall be any whit the worſe ſerued, but the better rather. For if they be wiſe according to the Word, that will make them wiſe in the world to: becauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is againſt or without that, is not onelie folly, but meere madneſſe. And therefore they that thinke and ſay, they will not be braue ynough, or ſufficiently glorious for Princes greatneſſe &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, they doe nothing indeed but paint out patched Princes, yea they ſtuffe them within and without, with that which is worſt; and neglect, and contemne, and in deſpightfull words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect that which is beſt. The very wiſe
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:6835:66"/>men among the Heathen, haue alwaies acknowledged, <hi>That nothing ſtandeth ſo vpright in the time of danger, nor continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo long, as a right, ſound, and relegious ſoule.</hi> And they haue told vs, <hi>That noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of courage, and gentleneſſe of ſpirit, is naturall to the gracious.</hi> Whereas if any ſuch thing be in the prowd, it is but bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, it is but baſtardly indeed. But we that haue beene brought vp in Gods ſchoole-houſe, ſhould proceed much further, knowing, beleeuing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, that God properly is ſaid to bleſſe the actions and the workes of the good only, alwaies <hi>ſetting himſelfe againſt the prowd,</hi> and caring for the humble and meeke, that ſo he may be againſt the one ſort in all manner of iuſtice and wrath: and with, and for the other, in all fauour and mercie, both of this life, and of that which is to come.</p>
               <p>And let this much ſuffice for the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate life of the king we treat of By pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate life I meane that which hee practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe, and cauſeth to bee practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by others that are about him in his
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:6835:67"/>court, at home, abroad, and elſewhere. But it is not ſufficient for a king, that as in regard of himſelf he be iuſt &amp; merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, neither yet that his houſe bee open to good and vertuous people, and ſhut againſt the wicked. Theſe are good things I confeſſe. And I would to God we might ſee theſe beginnings of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſo in them we might haue an aſſured teſtimonie of continuance and increaſe. But yet they are not all, neither muſt princes ſtay there, but proceed fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed, for though a Princes exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bee of verie great force and power, and that is it that we ſay commonly, <hi>All men frame themſelues</hi> to the kings exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: yet that is not all, wee muſt looke for more, and he muſt carefully accompliſh more, or cauſe it to bee accompliſhed. Hoe hath another perſon vpon him, and other duties to performe, beſides theſe common and generall duties of the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a Chriſtian. In which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding alſo he muſt go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before others, becauſe hee is aduaunced aboue others, <hi>For looke to whomſoeuer God hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:6835:67"/>much, of them will he require much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</hi> And therefore though I confeſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as I haue done alreadie, that his good example bee much, yea the verie ſame in his houſe &amp; kingdome, that the firſt mouer (as the Philoſophers vſe to ſpeake) is in Nature, which ſeemeth by his motion and turning, to draw vnto it ſelfe, and to carrie with it all the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior bodies: yet euen in them wee know that euery one of them hath by himſelfe his owne courſe and mouing, and the ſame ſometimes diuers, ſometimes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, wherevpon alſo wee ſee in the heauens ſo many configurations, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diuerſe aſpects, and the ſame ſundrie times deadly alſo. And ſo muſt it bee in all kingdomes &amp; politike bodies Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſarie that the Prince or King ſhould bee followed, yea that hee ſhould bee ſerued of all, ſeeing that hee raigneth ouer and for all. Howbeit, it will not therupon follow, that he ſhould not in his owne perſon exerciſe mercie and iudgement, or commaund it, and ſee it executed by thoſe that are vnder
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:6835:68"/>him. That goodneſſe which is incloſed in his perſon, muſt abound in his houſe, and muſt redound, and be ſpread abroad through his whole kingdome. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fountaine of mercie and iuſtice which is in himſelfe, the ſtreames (in a good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der running trom it) muſt ſpread them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the vtmoſt parts, by the means of ſuch officers as he ſhall chuſe and ſet in his eſtate, and make diſtributors of his vertue, therein as well anſwering his goodneſſe, as in their authoritie, parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his power. And therefore for our good and inſtruction <hi>Dauid</hi> addeth:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 6.</hi> Mine cies ſhall bee vnto the good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people of the land, that they may dwel or ſit with me. He that walketh in an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right way ſhall ſerue me.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee may behold in theſe few wordes the ſure eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a worldlie State and Kingdome, and alſo
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:6835:68"/>the conſtituting of a Princes good counſell. That other men may bee iuſt and mercifull, it is ſufficient that they themſelues haue theſe graces lodged and dwelling within them. But it is not ſo with a king or prince: for though he be iuſt and merciful in himſelfe, yet he is not iuſt or mercifull indeed, if he be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or to himſelf only. The reaſon is, be cauſe the king is not of himſelfe, nor for himſelfe, but conſiſteth of others as well as of himſelfe, and communicateth vnto others as well as to himſelfe, and indeed is ſet vp more for others than for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Wherefore hee muſt of neceſſitie be aſſiſted with councellors and officers: the weakeneſſe of his bodie, the wants of his mind, the greatneſſe and hardnes of his charge, and all, calleth therefore, that ſo in all good things generally, and in theſe two particularly, Mercie I mean and Iuſtice, and in all the parts and pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his kingdome, he may bee like to himſelf. A king perhaps may ſometimes imagine, that if he were alone, he ſhould raigne ſafely, he ſhould rule ſurely. But
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:6835:69"/>neſſe, retchleſneſſe, and weakeneſſe, when vnder pretext of adminiſtration of iuſtice, they create for Magiſtrates peeuiſh and peruerſe men, and vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of gouerning well, they ſet vp ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant perſons, and for pillars of their authoritie, they eſtabliſh ſuch as can do nothing that good is, and beſides are ſlaues to ſinne? Certainely, it is a hard if not an impoſſible thing, that the good neſſe of a Prince, though it be neuer ſo great, ſhould redreſſe and bring backe to good order ſuch bad choice. Nay rather it is to bee feared, that with great vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and a full ſwinge, they will carrie him and his ſtate away to euill and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, conſidering what great power and force euill hath, in and againſt all things, yea the good things of God. For the prince, for reſiſting of euil, &amp; to draw on to pood, hath no need to bee aided with ſuch people as hee muſt hale with himſelfe, and lift vp by force (for that were nothing elſe ſaue for his pleaſure ſake, to pull vpon himſelfe manifold burthens and dangers) but rather hee
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:6835:69"/>muſt haue men that will lend their ſhoulders, and bend their neckes, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, yea and more alſo, if need be: who will ſecond his good purpoſes, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort his ſore paines that are ſtaied and ſtrengthened againſt corruption, ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and violence: yet forſooth the other will thinke they haue wrought hard and ſore, ſpecially if good things fall out well, and come to good effect. So readie and naturall an inclination is there in men and matters to euill.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the Princes eies and care ſhould bee vpon the beſt ſort of people to ſet them in Offices, and beſtow char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vpon them. Hee will not giue thoſe places at hap hazard as we ſay, or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding either to his vnbridled or blind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: neither will hee beſtow them vpon thoſe whom he fauoureth moſt, or vpon the greateſt perſons, for that were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to make parties and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alities in his kingdome, and to create of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers for themſelues, &amp; not for his owne good, and the benefit of his people. And much leſſe will hee doe it for importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:6835:70"/>and ſuites ſake. But rather hee will take this courſe: Thoſe that ſhall affect ſuch places, he wil alwaies ſuſpect them, their perſons, and practiſes. For certaine it is, that he that very earneſtly aimeth at an office or liuing, hath laid his plot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie: and without doubt he deſireth it for the profit, &amp; not for the charge. And leaſt of all will a good Prince ſell ſuch places vnder any colour, whatſoeuer it be. For he knoweth, that he that buyeth is ſhrewdly prouoked, nay is after a ſort openly diſpenſed withall to ſell againe. If he be an exchequer man, hee will rob and ſpoile: if he haue to doe with iuſtice and judgement, he wil take preſents and bribes: if hee meddle with the matter of warte, or deale with gouernment, or any part of the ſtate, he will goe further: ſuch people will make ſmall account to ſell a ſtate, and to deliuer vp a kingdome. By ſuch breaches as theſe, hath all manner of miſcheefe entred into our land, and preuailed vpon all eſtates, ciuile, eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall, and all. I will adde but one word more, weknow but too much of theſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:6835:70"/>corruptions. And I would to God wee either knew or felt leſſe, vnleſſe we could make better vſe of them, for praier to God, for patience in ourſelues, and for all other good fruits beſides. The king that our Prophet ſpeaketh of, will for the auoiding of theſe miſcheefes, with his eies looke out into all the quarters and corners of his kingdome, and find eyes among them, making euerie where good people his eyes to ſee for him: and to informe him, hee will know, and haue in euery towne men of merite, and of ſeruice, I meane men of conſcience alſo as wel as of ſcience or skill. He will hold the reines in his hand, that he may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for ſuch, euen for euerie one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his profeſſion, and according to his degree. Shall any charge or place come to be void? The firſt thing he will doe, ſhall bee to goe and ſeeke out meet men for that place. And though they would hide them in their gardens, or amongſt the <hi>baggage &amp; ſluffe, as did Saul,</hi> or be at the cart, <hi>and follow the oxen,</hi> as did <hi>Eliſha,</hi> yet from thence will he fetch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:6835:71"/>and cauſe them to become exchequer men and treaſurers without deceit, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors without paſſion, and gouernours without faction, whoſe continuall care, &amp; mark that they ſhould aime at, ſhould be by gracious effects and fruits to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the good choice that their king had made of them. And though perhaps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had not deſerued, either the good report of vertuous people, or the grace and fauour of the faithfull Prince, yet now they would deſerue it, and that by all manner of well doing. And this is the reaſon why hee that hath ſaid in one place, <hi>that the king is the ſtay and ſtrength of the people,</hi> hath alſo ſaid in another place: <hi>the multitude of wiſe men is the ſaluation of the king,</hi> and the health of the world. And hee preſently telleth vs what this wiſdome is, <hi>the feare of God,</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>the fulneſſe, and the crowne, the beginning and the end of wiſdome.</hi> Becauſe verily to him that hath this fear of God, God, who is the full treaſure of all good things, will adde and giue graces ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for his calling, and of his own mercy
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:6835:71"/>and bleſſing will ſupplie all his lackes, and will cauſe his ſimplicitie rather ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare and breake forth than his ſubtlety; his libertie and freedome, rather than his diſſimulation; his weakeneſſe rather than another mans force; and all, that the glorie of the world may bee Gods and not mans. Whervpon it oftentimes followeth and falleth out, that the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter floriſheth in his ſeruant, <hi>as did Laban in Iacob, and Potipherah in Ioſeph,</hi> or to ſpeake more properly to the purpoſe, the king in his officer, <hi>as did Pharoah in Ioſeph:</hi> &amp; by conſequent the whole peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in ſuch a worthie inſtrument. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto which alſo <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, <hi>When the righteous are in authoritie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 29.2.</note> 
                  <hi>the people reioiceth: but when the wicked beareth rule, the people ſigh.</hi> Wherefore wee may ſafely conclude, that it doth by a manner of ſpeech infinitely import the Prince, the people, the Commonweale and all, to ſet vp in the ſame meet and worthie perſons, becauſe they be as it were the life and ſoule that holdeth all together, and without which the bodie it ſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:6835:72"/>not chufe, but languiſh and pine. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, before they can bee ſetled and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced there, they muſt be knowne. For as that is true, that of an vnknowne thing there is no deſire: ſo vertuous and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people cannot bee aduanced, vnleſſe they be firſt ſpied out. Now firſt and moſt aſſured make to know them by, is the feare of God, without which indeed all wiſedome eaſily degenerateth into craft and deceit, valour into violence, inſtice into priuate reuenge, policie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to priuate profit and monopolies, as we ſay, and as we haue ſeene in our age and land, where the wifeſt men haue beene ouertaken with couetouſneſſe, oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, briberie, and infinite numbers ſuch like. Yea without which alſo euen the verie beſt grace that God hath giuen vs, is an inſtrument of great euill and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, our affections breaking forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to paſſions, and reaſon it ſelfe a canſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cauillation and craft. And yet this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thing that is the leaſt ſought after, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt or greateſt number of Princes, &amp; which in the election or choice of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:6835:72"/>and publike officers, findeth as ſmall place and entertainement, as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie can be. Nay rather men ſay of ſuch, and it is receiued for a common ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, That theſe people are not folke fit for ſeruice: and that kings are great and mighte ynough, to bee ſerued alone without God: and that all that is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted and giuen to God, is abated and taken from their ſeruice. But fie vpon ſuch prophane and blaſphemous ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſo directly derogatorious to Gods glorie, <hi>Who alone muſt bee ſerued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 4.10.</note> and ſo peremptorily preiudiciall to Princes, Gods Lieutenants vpon earth: for is not this as much to ſay, that their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or Kings are Atheſts, <hi>&amp; without God in the world.</hi> They tell vs further, that thoſe that are ſtrict in conſcience, and tie themſelues to reaſon and to lawes, are not fit ſeruants for Princes. And their flatterers tell them they are aboue law, aboue nature, yea equall with God. What prophane? What blaſpemous ſpeeches are theſe? Is not this to defac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> equitie and honeſtie? To puffe vp fleſh
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:6835:73"/>and bloud to it owne confuſion, to eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate all humane ſocietie, if Princes may make and leaue lawes when they liſt. In ſuch caſes as theſe, the Apoſtle doth not without cauſe admoniſh, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.33.</note> 
                  <hi>Bee not deceiued, euill ſpeeches corrupt good manners.</hi> Yea verily the authour of veritie it ſelfe telleth vs,<note place="margin">Math. 6.24.</note> 
                  <hi>No man can ſerue two maiſters.</hi> And yet in another place the ſpirit ſayth,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pet 2.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Feare God, honor the king.</hi> By which wee may ſee, that theſe two maſters are not alwaies, and of their own nature contrarie (for if they were ſo, we could not obey them) and much leſſe are their ſeruices contrary. Nay rather they follow one vpon another, and come in their order and degree, as God firſt, the king after; and ſo Gods ſeruice firſt, and the Kings after. A vaſſal that ſerueth his proper Lord, is not for the dutie that he doth to him, a rebell to his Prince. No more is he diſobedient to God, that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his king, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding good things, and when and as he ſhould. Nay, I will ſay more: the vaſſale neuer better ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his Lord, than when hee faithfully
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:6835:73"/>ſerueth him that is king to both. And the reaſon thereof is plaine: not onely the vaſſale, but the lord himſelfe and all, owe the king all manner of homage and ſeruice. So none ſerueth the king ſo wel, as he that religiouſly ſerueth God, <hi>Who is lord of lords, and king of kings.</hi> It is too apparent in theſe daies, that the greateſt number of ſeruants ſerue not, but as we ſay, <hi>vnto the eie,</hi> and whileſt their maſters are preſent. And that is one reaſon amongſt many, why kings are ill ſerued by their ſeruants when they are far off, and are ſecretly betraied, when they are nigh. But ſuch as ſerue their king, and in doing of that dutie, are aſſured and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, that they ſerue God, they keepe alwaies one courſe: whether they bee nigh at hand or farre of, that is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, becauſe their obedience is not tied to place, but to perſons, and yet no further to perſons, than as in the feare and faith of God they may performe the duties they doe. And ſurely it muſt bee ſo with them, becauſe they ſerue to pacifie, appeaſe, and content their owne
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:6835:74"/>conſcience, and not to ſatisfie their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſight and eye alone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For if it bee ſo, the backe ſhall no ſooner be turned, but the hand will waxe idle, and the heart will be auerſe from the buſineſſe. No no, they haue alwaies God before their eies, and they know him to bee the beholder of their facts, more than of their faces, <hi>and the very ſearcher of their hearts and reines.</hi> From him they looke for their wages and hire, from him, yea from him alone they expect grace and fauor, being certainely aſſured that he will giue them a gracious recompence, though their Maiſters ſhould not, but ſhould <hi>bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind</hi> rather and <hi>froward.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.18.</note> From theſe trees then, and not from elswhere, muſt kings chuſe and fetch the graffes and ſciences of good Officers, of good ſubiects. But ſpecially hee muſt looke to haue from hence (as <hi>Dauid</hi> telleth vs here) good cornſellors of eſtate, whom they ſhould cauſe to fit neere and about themſelues, and make them partakers of their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, and of their power. For to keep and hold this burke or ſhip of the Common-weale
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:6835:74"/>(yea and of the church alſo) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, &amp; tight as we ſay, againſt all winds and blaſts, inward, outward, boyſterous, gentle, &amp;c. they muſt haue vpright and entire perſons, or elſe it will neuer bee. And reaſon, for being a ſound &amp; entire bodie, it muſt haue ſuch to guide &amp; tend it. Otherwiſe, if they be infected and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, they may put it, and all that is in it, in danger. And theſe are ſuch as muſt not carrie the rout, and beare the ſway in themſelues, nor keepe it for, or direct it to others, much leſſe lay it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people, whom they are to guide and gouerne, and leaſt of all vpon the Kings and Princes, who are but men, and many times muſt bee brought to good courſes, beeauſe they ſtray fowlie, but muſt referre all to the common good, and the benefit of the countrey &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which muſt continue, when they themſelnes, Princes, and all, ſhal be dead and rotten. Now againſt theſe good and faithfull people, whom hee will imploy &amp; vſe in publike place, he oppoſeth and ſetteth others, whom he will baniſh his
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:6835:75"/>houſe and kingdome, and preſence. And of them is it that he ſayth:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 7.</hi> He that ſhall vſe deceit, ſhall not dwell in my houſe: he that ſpeaketh a lie, ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine before me.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is that hee mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and ſayeth: Good and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people ſhall come into my clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet &amp; ſecret cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: they are they that I will be moſt familiar withall, and take beſt delight in. And good reaſon, for they are good, and will do me good, and my kingdome alſo, as I ſee by that auncient <hi>example of Ioſeph in Pharoahs ſtate.</hi> But the wicked ſhall be ſhut out of my houſe, yea they ſhall not come ſo much as into the vtmoſt court, for the verie gate it ſelfe ſhalbe ſhut againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And good reaſon alſo, for being naught themſelues, they will pollute the place, and defile the people, <hi>and a little leauen of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:6835:75"/>maliciouſneſſe and wickedneſse, ſoureth the whole lumpe.</hi> Yea hee meaneth more,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.6.</note> that good and vertuous people ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll haue ſeats and places of honour in his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, but the wicked ſhall not ſo much as ſtand in his preſence, but rather ſhall flie and fall downe before him, ſo ſmall hope ſhal they haue of preferment. And theſe wicked and vngodly men are deſcribed here by theſe two tearms, <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> both which he ſetteth againſt <hi>in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and a ſound way,</hi> mentioned in the laſt verſe before this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Deceit, is no other thing but indirect dealing and carriage, as in reſpect of mens actions and deeds: as lying alſo is nothing els but indirect deling, as in reſpect of ſpeech &amp; words. Both the one and the other of them are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to integrity or vprightnes: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the vprightneſſe of the hands, againſt which is oppoſed deceit; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſinceritie or vprightneſſe of our lippes, againſt which is oppoſed lying. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, theſe two amongſt other, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> witneſſes of the crookedneſſe and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectneſſe of our vnderſtanding and wils,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:6835:76"/>and to be ſhort, cleare witneſſes indeed, of that peruerſeneſſe and peeuiſhneſſe, which wee haue in our ſoules thorow ſinne. Yea both the one and the other of them are directly contrarie to that true wiſedome that ought to bee found in kings counſels. For ſayth the wiſe man, <hi>The wicked haue not ſeene it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccle, 15.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and that wiſedome holdeth her ſelfe alooſe from pride and deceit. Liers ſhal not ſo much as remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it.</hi> By all which we may ſee and learn, that it is not ynough to <hi>ſeeke after, and to purſue good things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.27.</note> 
                  <hi>but alſo we muſt flie from euill.</hi> Yea and not onely flie from euill, but alſo wee muſt chaſe &amp; driue it away, yea we muſt ſo liuely and ſpeedily chaſe it, that it may neuer bee able to gather ſtrength, or get footing: yea and wee muſt driue it ſo farre away, that it may neuer be able to hurt, hinder, or trouble any good thing. Here if in any thing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Phyſicians rules of flying from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>gue, are moſt meet to be practiſed, as ſoone, and as farre as may be, for this is a plague indeed. But the world is of a clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e contrarie mind, and foulie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:6835:76"/>in this behalfe. Manie deceiued <hi>with the pleaſures of ſinne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 11.25</note> 
                  <hi>which laſt but for a while,</hi> coll it, and imbrace it, as if it were vertue it ſelfe. Theſe are either ignorant in iudgement, or careleſſe in practiſe. Otherſome ſuppoſe, that good and euill are not contrarie, but may wel agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a houſe, in a kingdome, in a church. But why doe you not in nature compound fire and water; or in policie, peace, and warre; orin Gods church,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>the temple it ſelfe, and images?</hi> Surely they may as well and as ſoone make light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, heauen and hel, to agree together. Others imagine, that the good we haue, ſhould make vs hold our peace at the euill that moleſteth vs. But this is to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt our iudgement, as well as to tie our tongues and hands, and indeed by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent alſo defacing Gods graces in vs to rob him of his glory and praiſe. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat and particular perſons ſuppoſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are not to blamed, but excuſed rather when they are content to abſtaine from euill, or when they do in ſome ſore wink at it. And they imagine that this is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:6835:77"/>ſufficient, we haue no meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it, or to redreſſe it, and it hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſuch a head, that it is too great and ſtrong for vs to deale withal. Grant that to be good and true, yet if thou belong to God, hee hath giuen thee a heart to hate it, though not a hand to reforme it, &amp; he hath giuen thee a tongue to ſpeake againſt it, though not power to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it. To abſtaine from euill is well. But that is but the firſt ſtep to goodneſſe. And thou, if thou doeſt appertaine to God,<note place="margin">Hebr. 6.1. Rom. 12, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>muſt be carried forward towards per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi> He that ſayth, <hi>Abhorre that which is euill,</hi> preſently addeth, <hi>and be faſt glued to that which is good.</hi> Haſt thou vſed theſe good means? Doeſt thou vſe them? Haſt thou kept thy ſelfe free from the action and affection of euill? Thou doeſt well. But beware of blaunching and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, for that is not onely euill to thy ſelfe, but to infinite thouſands of ſoules beſides. And though to hurt thy ſelfe be much, yet to draw other with thee to the ſame ſin, &amp; by means thereof to the ſame condemnation, is much more greeuous.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:6835:77"/>
And though theſe things may bee ſome cloke for priuate perſons, yet ſuch neutralitie and halting betwixt two, is not or cannot bee iuſtifiable in a prince: nay they can haue no colour of it, or for it at all. God hath ſet him vp to puniſh it, and hath ſtrengthened him with his owne arme to repreſſe it: in his very face and countenance God hath grauen his owne Maieſtie, to aſtoniſh it, yea to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfit it, and driue it away. According to which <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe, who had good proofe thereof, ſayth,<note place="margin">Pro. 20.8.</note> 
                  <hi>A Prince that ſitteth in his throne of iuſtice, chaſeth away all euil with his eye.</hi> So that they that walke not according to this rule, anſwer not the end of their callings and offices, weaken Gods mightie power, put out his glorious Maieſtie, diſcourage the godlie, hearten the wicked, giue ſin the head, and a man cannot reckon vp the miſcheefs beſides. But on the other ſide, this ſhould be no ſmal comfort to godly kings and princes, and ſhould animate them, not to feare to puniſh the wicked, whatſoeuer accident to the contrarie
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:6835:78"/>either they themſelues might imagine, or other might propound vnto them for diſcouragement. And the rather hereof ſhould they bee well aſſured, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know that God will defend and maintaine <hi>his iustice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Chr. 19.6.</note> 
                  <hi>which they exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute:</hi> and ſet this before them, that ſith <hi>they adminiſter the iudgements of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God,</hi> and not their owne, hee that is <hi>iealous ouer his owne glorie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ichoſh. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and wil not giue it to another, cannot deſtitute them, neither will he forſake them for euer.</hi> But what ſhal we ſay, there is nothing more rife in all the courts of the world (whether they be thoſe that we cal Princes pallaces, or name ſeats of iuſtice) than wincking at euill, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which men paſſe to ſuffering of it, from ſuffering of it, they proceed to licentiouſneſſe in it, then they come to plead preſcription for it, to take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in it, to ſpeake for it vnder hand, to iuſtifie it openly, and at the laſt to ſet it vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> triumphant chariot, and ſo to bring it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o vſurpation and tyrannie. Such a hand, ſuch a head doth ſinne get: and ſuch ſower fruits doth winking at ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:6835:78"/>at the firſt, bring forth at the laſt. Men therefore ſhould bee wiſe to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the beginnings of euill. A little fire at the firſt beginning of it, might be put out with a handfull of duſt. But if that be neglected, and matter bee mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto it, it taketh hold of houſes, and burneth whole townes, and there can hardly bee found water or liquour to quench it, yea ſometimes it preuaileth againſt ponds and riuers. And who can maruell at this, that knoweth the nature of euill? It is corrupted in it ſelfe:it fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in all things, ſpecially humane and belonging to man, corruption, as fit matter to feed it, and for it ſelfe to work vpon. And do we not ſee, that ſomtimes a graine of ſome noiſome or poyſonfull thing, is powerfull againſt an ounce, againſt a pound, yea a whole lumpe of things of better complexion? One drop of poyſon, ſpecially of ſome very ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g poyſon, will preuaile vpon a tun of wine or water, yea euen vpon a very great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. One malicious man will get the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand of a whole councell yea of a
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:6835:79"/>whole ſtate. And many times a very meane man, if wee reſpect his qualities and graces, ſhall preuaile againſt the beſt and the greateſt. Our owne Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, and the ſtories of other nations, afford vs ſtore of ſuch bad examples. Many men will not ſtoope ſo low, as to regard theſe things. But they are to true notwithſtanding, for other mens imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations or exaltations, cannot euacuate truth, but it will alwaies remaine like it ſelfe. But what ſhal we ſay? vertue is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, yea careleſſely husbanded: and ſurely goodneſſe is tilled and dreſſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame meaſure and manner. Our humors fight againſt it, that is much: and our manners to, that is more: becauſe euil inward is leſſer offenſiue, than when it breaketh forth outwardly. Yea good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe euen in the beſt people (beſides the outward forces that are offred vnto it by the wicked) is beaten backe by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and as I may ſay, cooled within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, by the remainders of their owne ſinne, ſometimes by the malice of Satan: ſometimes by the ſlippings and fallings
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:6835:79"/>away of others: ſometimes, by the bad examples that are in the world: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the buffetings and beatings that the wicked vſe againſt it. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no maruell though it bee ſo backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in bearing and bringing forth fruit, when euen the very friends and louers of it doe giue it ſo cold a curry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and baſe entertainment, as it findeth at this day in the world.</p>
               <p>Wee may ſee then, that as well for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of euil, as heartening on to well doing, it greatly behoueth kings to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme theſe things that <hi>Dauid</hi> preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth here. Which they ſhall doe, if they as <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſet goodneſſe in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aboue euill, and place vertuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ouer and aboue the wicked. For howſoeuer euil be of it ſelfe ſhameleſſe, and as in regard of men, inſolent and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant; yet when it ſhall ſee it ſelfe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and goodneſſe aduanced, it will baniſh it ſelfe, yea vaniſh and flie away. Yea and this ſhall they the ſooner effect, if in their deeds, if in their words, they deteſt euill, and loue good, and if they
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:6835:80"/>they themſelues carrie in their faces and foreheads the marke and impreſſion of vertue, iuſtice, mercie, and ſuch like. For darkneſſe without doubt ſhall and muſt flie before light. And euen ſo euil, which is nothing but a priuation of good, as darkeneſſe is of light, if goodneſſe once appear, &amp; be eſtabliſhed, cannot hold his place, nor continue, or bee at all, where goodnes once entreth. But if it ſo fal out, thet a Prince come to gouernment and ſtate in an age ſo corrupt as ours is, and hee is not able to root out euill ſo ſoone as he would, or as he ſhould, this ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the leaſt, he muſt aduiſe and look to, that hee ſuffer it not to fall or drop vpon the more noble parts of the bodie (for if they be once taken, the other being ouertaken therwith, no part ſhal be free) but rather that he ſend it packing to the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeſt and furtheſt parts of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweale: euen as nature it ſelfe, in a naturall and humane bodie teacheth vs, expelling that which would annoy or hurt the vitals, as wee ſay, to the furtheſt parts, that ſo in that care and wiſedome
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:6835:80"/>the Prince may prouide, that it bee no part either of his ſence, or of his life, and leaſt of all certainely of his ſpirit, and of his ſoule. In a word, this is my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: The Prince ſhould not admit ſuch corruption, neither to his preſence, nor to his perſon, nor to his practiſe and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, nor commit vnto it his life, his councell, or eſtate: for if he doe ſo, hee hazardeth all, his bodie, his ſoule, his ſcepter, his kingdome, his ſubiects, &amp;c. And ſith this is the nature of naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſinne, that if it may be but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to preaſe into preſence, it will conceiue hope of further acceſſe and entertainement: mightie men muſt ſtop the paſſage of it, and ſhut their pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces gates, the eies and eares of their head, the power of their hands, the paſſions and affections of their hearts and whatſoeuer elſe, againſt it. But this is a verie great worke indeed for a Prince or King, I confeſſe it. But the perſon is great that is to doe it, and hee hath manie more meanes to effect it than meaner men, and therefore
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:6835:81"/>
                  <hi>taught his fingers to fight,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.1.</note> and made him able to ouercome all: yea and to inſtruct all Princes, preſent, and to come. (<hi>For whatſoeuer things are written beforehand,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> 
                  <hi>art written for our learning, that we thorow patience and comfort of the ſcriptures, might haue hope.</hi>) What courſe to keep, &amp; what remedie to vſe (ſpecially when they haue eſtabliſhed peace at home and abroad) for the redreſſing and the repreſſing ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of all euils, and particularly of ſuch, as either ciuile or forraine warres, haue ſet on foot in the kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 8.</hi> I will cut off <hi>(ſayth he)</hi> betimes all the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the land: that I may root out of the citie of the Lord, the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is as much in effect, as if he ſhould ſay: I will not put off from day to day, neither to frame mine owne life wel, nor by mine owne example to amend my
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:6835:81"/>people: for delaies are dangerous, ſpecially of good things, and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as wee ſay, is bald behind, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good taking hold of her forelockes: beſides, I haue no charter or patent of my life, and therefore I will not deferre the doing of this good. Neither will I for a long time, or many yeares, delay the reformation of my eſtate, but as much as in me lyeth, labour to bring it to a good condition ſpeedily. I know pother Princes are or will be of another mind, and that they may alleadge for themſelues many goodly clokes and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, as innouatian is dangerous, feare of the people, doubts and diffidences concerning the action it ſelfe, and diuers ſuch like. But I will caſt all theſe behind me, and make no account thereof: for the firſt is but a principle of Policie, and that is as vncertain, as mans braine that bred it. And for the ſecond, it hath ſmall force in it, and it may bee, ſpecially ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding for God, that when I fear moſt, I ſhall be moſt fauoured and followe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for he hath the hearts of men in his hand, to
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:6835:82"/>turne them at his pleaſure.</hi> And as for the third, concerning the action it ſelfe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine own hart telleth me it is good, and I am perſuaded thereof by the truth of the Word, why ſhould I lay, or ſuffer to lie ſtumbling blockes in my way? Nay rather thorow Gods goodneſſe and ſtrength, I will riſe vp ſo much the more earlie, and put my hand to that buſines, whatſoeuer may come of it. This is my full and flat reſolution. And ſith the lord by nature doth teach it me, I wil thorow his aſſiſtance and grace perform it. Doth not the ſunne, as ſoone as it riſeth, yea before it riſeth, driue and chaſe away darkeneſſe? And then why ſhould not I ſo ſoone as I aſcend to the ſcepter and throne, and come to the crown, perform theſe good things? Surely I will erect the throne of Iuſtice, certainely I will eſtabliſh pietie, vertue ſhall find enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement at my hands, and I wil baniſh vice. This did <hi>Dauid</hi> ſay, and this did he doe alſo. And in both theſe, it behoueth all good kings to reſemble him. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enterpriſe, and of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:6835:82"/>I confeſſe, ſpecially in this State and Kingdome, in which vice hath tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed a long time, nay in which it yet ruleth and beareth ſway. But yet if men will begin in time, the day is long, and there are many houres yet before night come. Delaies in other things are not good, but here they are ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke naught. Purpoſes will not ſerue, for they are but the imaginations of our mind: nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes neither, becauſe they are but bare words, and vttered many times to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue men: but practiſe &amp; performance is it that will glorifie God, and doe good to Church, Commonweale, Countrey, Kingdome, and all. The beames and ſtreams of a vertuous Prince, may make hote and comfort, and that without ouerheating or diſcomforting of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, his countrey, and kingdome: yea they may cauſe vertue to bud and ſpring, and they may nip vice in the head And why ſhould wee doubt of it? Seeing wee know that Gods graces, though in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat perſons, ſhall not yet bee vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, much leſſe ſhall they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> without
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:6835:83"/>life in men that reſemble his Maieſtie, and beare his marke vpon them. His Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diake as we may ſay, is furniſhed: a man may ſee it planted with much goodnes: he is not yet at the midſt of his age, and if God would, wee might ſee all things in the Kingdome and Commonweale changed into better: the ſores thereof ſtrengthened and healed, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any wound or ſcar: the former euils ſoftened, yea almoſt worne out of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, and as it were quite and cleane forgotten. And though it were ſo, that the greateſt part of a Princes life were paſt, yet that ſhould not hinder redreſſe and amendment of matters. The more that hath ben neglected in former time, die more ſhould be reformed in the reſt of the daies of the pilgrimage that wee are to liue. Who knoweth whether God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> granted life to that end? That ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ding to the breaches of our former y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ares, our liues might bee more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to him, and profitable to the people, and our liues and our deaths to, more comfortable to our ſelues. Sure wee are
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:6835:83"/>of this,<note place="margin">Eccle. 5.16.</note> that God commandeth vs <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme the ſeaſon,</hi> and rendreth this reaſon of it, <hi>for the daies of euill.</hi> And wee know this is a ſure note of excellent bleſſing from God vpon his people: <hi>they ſhall bring forth fruit in their age,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 92.14.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhal be ſat and flouriſhing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet I meane not for all this, that Princes vnwiſely, or without aduiſe, ſhal cut off, burne, ſeare, or as we ſay in plain Emgliſh, without conſultation run into and ſet open alterations and changes of ſtate, execution of iuſtice, &amp;c. for ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in ſeeking to ſettle good, and to auoid euill, they might fall into a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheefe, more intollerable by much than their preſent condition In nature we ſee that ſuch a humane bodie there may be, as in which all the bloud ſhall be ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, that before a man ſhould find any good bloud therein, he might (if he wuld vſe phlebotomie or bloud letting) draw out and take away both the life &amp; the laſt drop together. In ſuch a caſe, when the corruptions are ſo groſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd infinite, a skilfull Phyſician will vſe Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſis,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:6835:84"/>as they call it, or labour to bring it to a better temperature or mixture of the humours. He will draw from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die I confeſſe, both by diuerſe meanes, and at diuerſe times, but yet he will take no more but what is needfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to vnburthen Nature of. Which when it is diſcharged indeed, gathereth vigorand force vnto it ſelfe againe, and euaporateth and euacuateth by ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and other good meanes, the reſt of the poyſon or maligne humours: and to be ſhort, doth by this gentle euacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſundring euil from good, make good indeed at the length the verie bloud it ſelfe. And euen ſo muſt the Prince doe in this abundance of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and corrupt humors in the State or Commonweale. There may bee in a kingdome ſometimes ſuch maligne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and ſuch ſtore of poyſonfull corruption, that though the Prince would willingly purge the euill in that eſtate, yet wanes at home and abroad, plagues, famines, and a number ſuch like peſtilences within the boſome of the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:6835:84"/>Commonweale, will not ſuffer him to doe it. If he ſhould open a veine, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit would depart with the bloud, and the life would goe away with the ſtrength. What muſt he doe then? Countenance euill? At no hand. Shall hee wincke at tranſgreſſion? Not ſo neither. Shall hee diſgrace and keepe backe from prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the good and vertuous? Be it and all the reſt farre from him. For the firſt is to commit ſinne with a high hand,<note place="margin">Deut. 29.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Lord will not be mercifull to ſuch.</hi> The ſecond is to ſuffer it to get a head, and when it is once aloft, it will hardly or not at all bee beaten downe. And the third is to wound, yea to breake the hearts of the faithfull, who the more they bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, the more doe the wicked pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile. What then? He muſt as hee may, take away from the wicked and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie all their gouernement and authari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for they are not men meet for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it being a holie and a heauenlie thing, it muſt haue men to exerciſe it, that do in ſome ſort ſort with the nature thereof. On the other ſide, hee muſt, raiſe
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:6835:85"/>vp good people from vnder their yoke and burthen, hee muſt deuide amongſt them his fauour, his authorities, his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, for they only are both worthie of them, and fit for them, becauſe God and not man, by ſhedding his graces into their hearts, hath made them meet ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. This if they would doe, they ſhould in a ſmall time ſee by this diſcretion, and thorow Gods bleſſing vpon their care a conuerſion or turning of their State, without any ſubuerſion, nay without any great great trouble to it or in it: and a new kingdome, yet without any great noueltie or change. The ſhip of Delos, ſo much read of, and celebrated in anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, for laſting many yeares and ages without renewing, whence got it that fame, but becauſe that ſo ſoone as a lord or planet was in danger, they diligently and preſently prouided another in the roome thereof. And euen ſo, if a King will amend an eſtate or kingdome that is deca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, he muſt proceed by the ſame courſe: If ſo ſoone as a dignitie, ſtate, or office ſhall be void, he be careful to haue
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:6835:85"/>it repleniſhed with good and vertuous people, and ſuch as are fit for the charge, hee ſhall within leſſe than tenne yeares make all new, and yet without innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea hee ſhall doe it by an encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that ſhall not bee perceiued, till God make it breake forth, and ſo ſhall bring backe pietie and iuſtice to their auncient glorie, and ſhall beget againe in the hearts of his ſubiects, vertue, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, loyaltie, and euery good thing beſides, ſpecially if euerie one in his Countrey, in his Colledge, in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, in his Towne, according as hee hath beene choſen by the Prince, to a good place, ſhall bring to this good worke the ſame good affection, and ſhall ſet it forward after the ſelfeſame maner. But if on the other ſide, hee ſet vp in the roome of a wicked man a wicked ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor: if he prouide for the place by lot as wee ſay, or beſtow it vpon him that will offer moſt, or giue it for importunitie, or for fauour, then I can ſay no more but this, The good that was done in nine moneths, will bee ouerthrowne in three
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:6835:86"/>daies. For this wee may aſſure our ſelues of, an eſtate or a building decayeth in fewer daies than there was of yeares ſpent to reare it vp, and eſtabliſh it. So true is that ſaying of the Philoſopher, It is more eaſie to deſtroy than to build.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the king that wee treat of, ſeeing hee is fallen into ſuch a wicked age, will begin his worke earely in the morning: euen as ſoone as hee entreth, ſo ſoone will hee begin, becauſe hee is perſuaded that God hath aduaunced him to that end. And our Sauiour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth, <hi>Firſt ſeeke the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 6.33.</note> 
                  <hi>and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and then all theſe things ſhall be giuen vnto you.</hi> And hee will, doe it alſo euen with the ſame hart and affection that <hi>Dauid</hi> did, that is, <hi>that he might purge and reforme the citie of his God:</hi> and he will not doe it that he might raigne quietlie and at his eaſe, for that is but a priuate and worldly thing, and not thankes worthie; but that the Lord might rule and raigne in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate and Kingdome, and that hee mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ee religiouſlie and holilie ſerued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:6835:86"/>church. For let men thinke and ſay what they liſt, it is for the churches ſake alone, (which God hath euerlaſtingly loued, euen from before all worlds) that he vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth and maintaineth this world. For the Churches ſake hee preſerueth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies, Commonweales, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, which are rather the Innes as I may ſo call them, than the houſes of the church, that warfa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth and trauaileth to and fro in the world: which otherwiſe wee might account (ſauing that by their groſſeneſſe and thiekneſſe, they ſhelter and couer the precious fruits that God hath put into them) not very profitable, ſpecially as in regard of godlineſſe. And yet notwithſtanding, this is the Church that is ſuſtained and maintained by God for his onely ſonnes ſake, who hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red death for it, euen Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour, and notwithſtanding <hi>is the king of kings,</hi> vnder whom of neceſſitie, all the kings of the world muſt bow, and for whom it is that they muſt raigne, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting down, at the very feet of his croſſe, becauſe in that hee triumphed, their
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:6835:87"/>crownes, their diademes, and their ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſpecially if they deſire to raigne in bleſſedneſſe ouer their ſubiects in the world, and would one day raigne for all eternitie in the heauens, without which they are more miſerable than the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of men, <hi>Becauſe for mighty men there are mightie torments prepared,</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Iſaih</hi> in expreſſe tearmes ſayth: <hi>Tophet is prepared of old,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 30.33</note> 
                  <hi>it is euen prepared for the king: he hath made it deep &amp; large: the burning thereof is fire and much wood, the breath of the Lord like a riuer of brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone doth kindle it.</hi> In a word then as it were, or ſhort ſumme to ſhut vp all, and to conclude with <hi>Dauid:</hi> Our king will frame his ſoule to Mercie and to Iuſtice. From his perſon they ſhall run, and flow into his court, into his counſell, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence they ſhall ſpread themſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r all the members of his ſtate, euen vnto the very borders &amp; vtmoſt bounds of his kingdome. <hi>All his waies,</hi> in a word, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> according to Gods own example,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhal be Iudgement and Mercie.</hi> But becauſe that the bodie is made for the Church,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:6835:87"/>he will with all his heart giue himſelfe to the ſtudie of truth, and be very mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of and carefull for the ſeruice of God, and will referre all that hee hath or may haue, to the defence and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to the reſtauration and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Church, the rareſt iewel that God hath vouchſafed to make ſhine in the world.</p>
               <p>O God which haſt from before all times appointed our king to bee borne in ſo troubleſome a time and wicked age, as wherein the ſtate is rent by factions, the Church is troubled with ſchiſmes, and the moſt wiſe ſee nothing but dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the ſame ſo thicke, as no eye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nay no diſcourſe is able to pierce it much leſſe to driue it away; double in theſe double miſcheefes and euils, thy bleſſed annointing, euen thy holy grace vpon him. Poure vpon his head the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of thy ſeruant <hi>Dauid,</hi> yea double and treble that bleſſed ſpirit of thine vpon him, that vnder him we may once agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſee our State eſtabliſhed, and thy church
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:6835:88"/>gathered together, that ſo vnder thee by his meanes, wee may with one accord ſing, as thy holie Angels did and doe, <hi>Glorie bee to God in the moſt high places, and in earth peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and towards men good will:</hi> and that I my ſelfe might then ſay, though it were euen at this preſent houre, <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.29.</note> 
                  <hi>according to thy word, ſeeing that mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>So be it.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:6835:88"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
